music
music
are still here listening to this speech
都還在這裡聽這個演講
It takes a lot of enthusiasm
要有相當的熱情才有辦法
so first of all congratulations
所以首先向各位致意
Our lecture today is sponsored by the Institute of Culture and Philosophy, Academia Sinica
我們今天的講座是由中研院文哲所
Director Hu Xiaozhen
所長胡小真所長
to give a lecture
來主講
Director Hu is one of the youngest directors of Academia Sinica
胡所長是中研院目前最年輕的所長之一
It should be the youngest
原來應該就是最年輕
But I don't know that the director of the chemistry department may be younger than you
但是我不知道化學所所長可能比你還年輕
Then the famous rich woman
那麼是有名的財女
Rich women are also one of the subjects of his research
財女也是他研究的主題之一
Director Hu is a graduate of National Taiwan University
胡所長是臺大溫習畢業
Then go to the UCC Provincial Union to study for a master's degree
接著就到UCC省聯盟讀碩士
Then went to Harvard University to get a Ph.D.
然後到哈佛大學得了博士
This is what a rich woman should have.
這個都是一個財女應有的這個
Then his research direction
那麼他研究的方向
related to women
跟女性比較有關係
his three directions
他的三個方向
The first is young women's literature
第一個是年輕的女性文學
I think you have many
我想各位有不少
may have noted his famous book in this regard
可能已經注意到他的這方面的一本名著
It is inevitable for a rich woman to test her career
財女測業未免
The Scheming of Modern Chinese Women's Narrative Literature
近代中國女性敘述文學的心機
It was in early 2003
是2003年初的
His second principle is
他的第二個原則是
Re-exploring the conflict and fusion between Ming and Qing literature and modern literature
重新探索明清文學跟近代文學之間的衝突跟融合
Under this topic, he wrote a book "Society where mental ideals and physical strength cannot be amnesiac".
在這個題目下他寫了一本《心理想就體力不可失憶之社會》
This book was published in 2011
這一本書在2011年出版
get 2012 soon
很快就得到2012年
Academia Sinica's first Humanities and Social Sciences Special Book Award
中研院第一屆人文社科學的專書獎
The third direction of research is his recent research
第三個研究的方向是他近期的研究
I haven't seen any literature on this
這方面我還沒有看到相關的著作
But maybe already, I don't know
不過可能已經有了我不知道
It is to study the presentation of Southwest China by young literati
是研究年輕文人對中國西南地區的這個呈現
Well, there are very few researchers on this topic
那麼這個題目研究人很少
must be interesting
一定是很有意思的
Chief Hu has received many honors including this
胡首長曾經獲得到過許多的榮譽包括這個
Youth of Academia Sinica in 1999
1999年中研院的青年
Scholar Research Work Award
學者研究著作獎
2003 Wu Daer Award of the National Science Council
2003年國科會的吳大兒獎
And the 2012 I just reported to you
還有剛才我跟各位報告的2012年的
The First Humanities and Social Sciences Special Book Award
第一屆人文社科學專書獎
He also invited the International Conference of Japanese Orientalists in Japan
他也禍邀在日本的國際日本東方學者會議
The keynote speech
關係那一場發表專題演講
This is also an honor that is not easy to get.
這也是一個很不容易得到的榮譽
The topic of Mr. Hu's speech today is Chinese women's travel experience
胡首長今天會演講的題目是中國女性的旅行經驗
From Ming and Qing Dynasties to Early Ming Dynasty
從明清到明初
I think this topic is quite interesting
我覺得這個題目相當有意思
Because ancient women seem to travel less
因為古代的女性好像比較少旅行
so this is a
所以這是一個
Research in this area is not easy
這方面的研究本來就比較不容易
The second trip is a very attractive thing for many people
第二個旅行對很多人來講是非常吸引人的一件事情
I am a colleague of the History Institute of China-Ireland Studies
我是中愛研究的歷史研究所的同仁
We used to have an old director
我們以前有一位老所長
He is now in his 80s
他現在已經80幾歲了
I asked him why did you devote yourself to history?
我問他你為什麼會投身歷史呢
He said that when he was studying in Yizu School in Nanjing
他說他在南京讀宜族學校的時候
My favorite is to go to a small hotel at the front to see the registration department of the hotel
我最喜歡的是到前面的一個小旅館去看旅館的登記部
Registry Department
上面都會登記部
from where to where to go
從哪裡來到哪裡去
its history is not
它歷史不就是
Let's learn where we come from and where we go
讓我們學習從哪裡來到哪裡去
So it has since decided to study history
所以它從此以後決定學習歷史
so this story i keep telling
所以這個故事我一直講
In the future, when I write an article, I should start with this
將來我寫一篇文章應該把這個作為開頭
so travel
所以旅行這個事情
travel hotels etc. are very
旅行旅館等等都是很
big has a lot of imagination
大有很多想像的
very interesting topic
很有意思這個題目
so i think many people come today
所以我想今天很多人來
It's all because he was deeply attracted by Chief Hu's personal dismissal
都是因為深受胡首長個人的裁學的吸引
and the attraction of this topic
以及這個題目的吸引
I won't say much now
那我現在就不多說
We now welcome Chief Hu with applause
我們現在以掌聲歡迎胡首長
ask yuma
請問尤瑪
Just now Dean Wang Fei mentioned
剛才王飛院長已經提到了
Today is such a wet and cold winter day
今天是這麼濕冷的冬日
and still this
而且還是這個
It's Friday night, the eve of the holiday.
就是假期前夕禮拜五的晚上
Well in fact I just got
那麼事實上我剛剛接到
This task in the courtyard
院裡面的這個任務
I don't know the seriousness of this matter
我还不知道这事情的严重性
I just know it's the end of December
我只知道是12月底
I found out later that it was December 24th
后来才发现这是12月24号
I thought to myself that this task is too difficult.
我心里想这个任务未免也太艰巨了
So how can we have a topic that can attract everyone?
那么要怎么样能够有一个题目可以吸引大家
How about coming to Academia Sinica on such a day?
在这样的一个日子前来中研院呢
So the vice president just mentioned
那么所以刚才这个副院长提到了
Chinese women in our impression
中国女性在我们的印象当中
Isn't it very fulfilling?
不是不太履行的吗
so let's talk
所以呢我们就来谈一谈
Chinese Women's Fulfillment Experience
中国女性的履行经验
Surely this deceitful subject
肯定就能把这个骗人的题目
You can fool everyone
就可以把大家给骗过来了
So obviously it seems to have had some success
那么显然好像还是有一点成功的
So
那么
Although my topic is customized
虽然说我的题目定做的是
Chinese Women's Fulfillment Experience
中国女性的履行经验
But I really have to start by saying
但是我真的必须一开始就得说
There's absolutely no way this speech can be put together for you.
这个演讲绝对不可能为各位整理
Or crawling books or talking about
或者是爬书或者是纵论
This millennium or this hundreds of years
这个千年或是这个几百年以来
of Chinese women's experience with this fulfillment
的中国女性的这个履行的经验
no way to do a full description
没有办法做一个完整的描述
Of course, a big reason for this is that
当然这很大一个原因是
i'm not a historian at all
我根本就不是一个历史学家
I'm actually noticing
在做其实我很注意到
this historian is doing
这个历史学家在做
makes me feel very nervous
讓我覺得非常的緊張
i am not a historian
我不是一個歷史學者
There is no way to do this description historically
沒有辦法做歷史性的這個描述
So what should I say I really want to talk about?
那麼應該說我真正希望談的呢
Is it a woman who travels
是並不是女性誰去旅行了
how to travel
怎麼去旅行了
What means of transportation did you use to travel?
用什麼交通工具去旅行了
where did you travel
去了哪裡旅行了
Or must have seen something, etc. These questions
或者是一定看到了什麼等等這些問題
because I study literature
因為我是研究文學的
what i want to talk about
我希望談的問題呢
It should be said that it is a literary work, how to write it
應該說是文學作品去怎麼寫
this woman's journey
這個女人的旅行
And when the woman's trip actually happened
而當女人的旅行真的發生的時候
What about this trip and his writing
這個旅行呢又對於他的文字
What effect will it have?
會產生什麼樣的作用呢
This is the question I want to know
這個才是我想要知道的問題
So today I will talk about a special woman
那麼今天呢我會圍繞著一個特殊的女性來談
from her life
從她的生活
From her travel experience
從她的旅行的經驗
And her writing in the mail?
還有她的郵寄的書寫呢
start as core
開始為核心
then spread out
那麼開展出去
Trying to describe my travels with Chinese women
試圖陳述一個我對於中國女性的旅行
An Observation on the Problem of Travel
旅行這個問題的一個觀察
well then
好 那麼
sorry
對不起
Okay, so let's start with this twentieth-century
好 那麼我們就先從這個二十世紀一位
once very very famous one
一次非常非常著名的一個
Women's Tour Begins
女性的旅遊開始
so who is this woman
那麼這個女性是誰呢
Her name is Lu Bicheng
她叫做呂碧成
Lu Bicheng was born in 1883
呂碧成是1883年生的
Then the one who died in 1943
那麼1943年去世的
So it's basically this pro-Wo Mingchu period guy
所以基本上就是這個親沃明初時期的人
Then she was really famous at the time
那麼她是當時真是鼎鼎大名的一個
a rich woman writer
一個財女作家
also an educator
也是一個教育家
also a tourist
也是一個旅遊家
Then her life is very, very wonderful
那麼她的人生是非常非常精彩的
We can almost say there's something about her
我們幾乎可以說有關於她的事情呢
It's just that nothing is ordinary
就是沒有一件事情是平凡的
Her life is spent with extraordinary
她的一生就是用不平凡
to define
來定義的
Then she was born in Anhui
那麼她的出生呢是這個安徽
This is still my same
這還是我的同
Datong Township
大同鄉
A late man in Anhui, one key family
安徽的一個晚男的一個一個關鍵的人家
So we can say that her early life
那麼我們可以說她早年的生活
is a standard Guixiu
是一個標準的歸秀
Like those mentioned in my previous research
就像是我之前的研究裡面所提到的那些
The Guixiu rich girl in the Ming and Qing Dynasties is the same
明清時期的歸秀財女一樣
she was born in a good family
她生在一個很好的家庭
Father is an official, mother knows how to take care of books and is literate
父親當官 母親知書打理 識字
teach her to read and write
教她看書寫字
There is a very good private library in the house
家裡面有一個很好的私人的Library
She can study golden shit by herself since she was a child
她可以從小就自己去研讀金屎
Probably such a background
大概是這樣的一個背景
But what?
不過呢
Lu Licheng, she is more unfortunate
呂立誠她比較不幸的是
Her father died when she was very young
她的父親在她很小的時候就過世了
Then there were some disputes in her family.
那麼她家族裡面發生了一些紛爭
So they can no longer gain a foothold in their hometown
所以他們沒有辦法再在自己的家鄉立足下去
then her mother wants
那麼她的母親希望
Lu Licheng can live and work in peace
呂立誠可以安身立命
further education is available
可以得到進一步的教育
sent Lu Licheng to her uncle's house
就把呂立誠送到了她的舅舅家
Where is this uncle's house?
這個舅舅家在哪裡呢
In a place called Tanggu
在一個叫做唐姑的地方
Of course this is not far from Tianjin
那當然這個就是離天津不遠
So obviously Lu Licheng is there
那麼顯然呂立誠在那裡
She continues to grow her this
她繼續的增長了她的這個
this classical aspect of this
這個古典方面的這個
Ability to read and write
閱讀寫作各方面的能力
But when he was about 20 years old
不過當他到了20歲左右的時候
He has a renewed desire
他有了一個更新的想望
what is this wish
這是什麼想望呢
It is that he hopes to go to a bigger place
就是他希望可以到更大的地方去
go and see
去看看
what happened in the new place
新的地方發生了什麼事情
Especially new women's schools
特別是新的女性的學校
Appeared in China at this time
這個時候在中國出現了
What do women's schools teach?
那女性的學校在教些什麼呢
Lu Bicheng has a new wish in her heart
呂碧成心中有了一個新的想望
so he decided
所以呢他決定
to the nearest big city
要到離他最近的一個大城市
That is Tianjin to see
那就是天津去看看
What is the so-called new style of women's school?
所謂新式的女學是怎麼一回事
Then at this time he received
那麼這個時候他受到了
resistance of very very large families
非常非常大的家庭的阻力
that is his uncle
也就是他的舅舅
with a more traditional way of thinking
用一個比較傳統的思維
of course stop him
當然就阻止他去
Then this Lu Bicheng
那麼這個呂碧成
seems for the record
好像根據記錄
He's been a boy since he was little
他從小就是一個比較像男孩子的
a girl
一個女孩
It is more dispatchable
就是比較派遣性強
So he was so angry
所以呢他竟然就一氣之下
just ran away from home
就離家出走了
What's even more frightening?
更可怕的是呢
when he ran away from home
他離家出走的時候
bring nothing
什麼都沒有帶
according to his own statement
根據他自己的自述
he confiscated the luggage
他沒收行李
no money
也沒有帶錢
I got on the train alone
就一個人就上了火車
going to tianjin
要到天津去
Then this may well be the beginning of a tragedy
那麼這很可能是一個悲劇的開始
right
對不對
But Lu Bicheng is still very lucky
不過呂碧成他還是很幸運的
he is on this train
他在這個火車上面
met a
就結識了一位
A nobleman who helped him a lot
對他幫助很大的貴人
who is this person
這個人是誰呢
Let's see Lu Bicheng's life
我們看呂碧成的生命
from this time on
從這個時候開始
Just have an indissoluble bond with Lu Xingjie
就跟呂星傑下不解之緣
Who is this noble man he knows?
他認識的這個貴人是誰呢
It is a famous hotel in Tianjin
是天津的一個停留名的旅館
Mistress of Fozhaolou
叫做佛兆樓的女主人
So
那麼
And we also found that Lu Bicheng
而且我們也發現呂碧成
He obviously has an innate ability
他顯然天生有一個能力
He can explain different people on the journey
他能夠在旅途上面去解釋不一樣的人
if i guess if i were on the train
如果我猜如果是我在火車上的話
I might just go all the way to the empty city
我可能就一路就空城就到
just no one cares about me
就是沒有人會理我
But Lu Bicheng is on the train
但是呂碧成他在火車上
be able to explain to a stranger
就能夠解釋一個陌生人
and help him
而且對他提供幫助
so what
所以呢
This Lu Bi achievement follows this
這個呂碧成就跟著這個
Fozhaolou Hotel
佛兆樓這個旅館的
The proprietress has arrived in Tianjin
老闆娘到了天津
And what?
而且呢
The hostess also introduced him
這個女主人還幫他介紹了
a more important person
一個更重要的一個人
It's Lu Bicheng
是呂碧成
Who was it? That was from the Tianjin Ta Kung Pao at that time.
是誰呢 那就是當時天津大公報的
This is like saying boss
這個等於說老闆
Eagle chain weaving
叫做鷹華鷹鏈織
So what about this eagle chain weaving?
那麼在這個鷹鏈織呢
After reading this letter that Lu Bicheng offered to him,
讀到了這個呂碧城主動提供給他的
What about after the poem?
詩文之後呢 大為擊賞
He said such a young girl
他說這麼年輕的女孩子
able to write such a good article
能夠寫這麼好的文章
very very touched
非常非常的感動
So what about this eagle chain weaving?
於是呢 這個鷹鏈織呢
Just ran to this Fozhao Tower to find Lu Bicheng
就直接跑到這個佛兆樓來找呂碧城
And what about inviting him to write for this Ta Kung Pao
並且呢 邀約他為這個大公報
writing
寫作
So from now on, what about Lu Bicheng?
那麼從此開始呂碧城呢
It's like starting to explore the world in Tianjin
等於說就是在天津開始闖天下了
So he started writing for this paper?
那麼他開始為這個報刊寫作啊
be an editor, wait
當編輯啊等等
so because of
那麼由於呢
He is so rich
他實在是這個財氣太大了
What I wrote made a lot of this
寫的東西呢 讓非常多當時的這個
this text
這個文
This is it
就是這個
celebrity
社會名流啦
This man of letters
這個文人財子啊
are very very shocked
都非常非常的受到震撼
So he quickly
所以呢 他很快的就
In the area of ​​Beijing and Tianjin
在北京天津一帶呢
want to be very famous
想有非常大的名氣
He also had contacts with many famous literati
也跟很多很有名的文人有所來往
Everyone sees this time
各位看到這個時候就是
When I first arrived in Tianjin and entered Ta Kung Pao
剛剛到天津進入大公報的時候的
On the left is Lu Bicheng
左邊的是呂碧城
The one on the right is the lady of the theater
右邊的就是影院之的夫人
I'm sorry, is there a problem?
對不起 有問題嗎
OK good
OK 好
Lu Bicheng had some other experiences after this
在這個之後呂碧城還有一些其他的經歷
He once entered Yuan Shikai's government
他曾經進入過袁世凱的政府
served as Yuan Shikai's secretary
擔任袁世凱的秘書
And a more special experience is
而更特別的經歷是
in 1906
在1906年的時候
In fact, he was in his early 20s at this time.
事實上這個時候他才20出頭
only 23 years old
也才不過23歲
In our case, a college graduate
在我們來說就是一個大學畢業生
but he has accepted
但是他已經接受了
It is equivalent to accepting Yuan Shikai's commission
等於說接受了袁世凱的委託
went to do one
去辦了一個
It is considered a very early high school in the north
在北方算是很早期的一個高等的學堂
beiyang woman
叫做北洋女子
It is a model school
是示範學堂
And what?
而且呢
He soon became the school's
他很快的就當了這個學校的
called supervision
叫做監督
That's what we mean today
那就我們今天的意義來說
It's the principal
就是校長了
so what
所以呢
What about Lu Bicheng in the 1910s
在這個1910年代的這個呂碧成呢
He is actually a
他其實是以一個
Educator Identity for Girls' Education
女子教育的教育家的身份
such an image appears
這樣的形象出現的
good
好
then but
那麼不過
During this time he wrote a lot
在這段時間他雖然寫了很多
sing girl
提唱女學呀
What is this song about saving the country and the people?
這個唱導什麼救國救民啊
what kind of articles
什麼這類的文章
But what?
不過呢
He didn't actually play such a role.
這樣的角色他其實並沒有扮演的
too long
太久
after a few years
過了幾年之後呢
He left the circle
他就離開了這個圈子
then start
那麼開始
Another image appeared
那另外一個形象出現了
he arrived in shanghai
他到了上海
Become a foreign businessman like this
變成一個跟這個洋商啊
what a person doing business
什麼做生意的一個人
And what?
而且呢
lady is very smart
小姐人非常的聰明
he is fast
他很快的
really made money
就真的賺到了錢
living a very luxurious life
過著非常這個豪奢的生活
And what?
而且呢
after this
在這個之後呢
He started to have some travel experience
他就開始有了一些旅行的經驗
then compare
那麼比較
we may be able to say unbelief
我們或許可以說不信的事
After this Lu Bicheng can even say
在這個之後呂碧成甚至可以說
She's been homeless all her life.
她是一生就真的就無家了
She keeps wandering in different places
她就不斷地在不同的地方漂泊著
because of some other special factors
因為這樣一些其他的特別的因素
We don't have time here so I won't mention it
我們在這邊沒有時間就不提了
In fact, Lu Bicheng has never been married in his life.
呂碧成事實上是一輩子都沒有結婚的
So I guess it doesn't have to be in the same place as her
所以我想這跟她可以不必定在一個地方
Then walking around still has a certain relationship
然後到處行走還是有一定的關係的
Then from 1918 to 1922
那麼在1918到1922年的時候
Of course, everyone think about this time
當然這個大家想想這個時間
The May Fourth Movement was in 1919
那個五四運動是1919年
Then when she was from 1918 to 1922
那麼她在1918到1922年的時候
That is, before and after the May 4th News Movement
也就是五四新聞化運動前後的時候
Lu Bicheng went to Columbia University in New York to audit and study
呂碧成到了紐約的哥倫比亞大學去旁聽去讀書
Let's take a look, this is Lu Bicheng from the Columbia period
我們來看看這是哥倫比亞時期的呂碧成
Can you imagine this is an international student?
可以想像這個是留學生嗎
So where does this claim come from?
那麼據說這個根據是哪裡來的呢
In fact after his death
事實上是在他世事以後
There are records left by some religious friends who have been with him
有跟他有過交往的一些宗教上面的朋友所留下來的紀錄
So it is said that after Lu Bicheng arrived in New York?
那麼據說這個呂畢成到了紐約之後呢
where does he live he doesn't live in a school dormitory
他住在哪裡他不是住在學校的宿舍
He might not even have a formal semester
他搞不好也沒有正式的學期
He lives in a big hotel in a big hotel in New York
他居住在紐約的大飯店裡面大旅社裡面
And it is said that this Lu Bicheng's room where he lived
而且據說他所住的這個呂畢成的房間呢
Incredibly big
大得不得了
The rent in this hotel is the most expensive in the whole hotel
這個在旅館裡面的房租是整個旅館裡面最貴的一間
What if the average Westerner lives in such a place?
如果說是一般的西方人住在這樣的地方的話呢
Only stay for about a week at most
最多就不過住個一個星期左右
maybe there's no money left
可能就已經沒有錢了
But where did Lu Bicheng live at that time?
可是呂畢成當時住在那裡呢
But you can live here for six months
卻可以一住就住了六個月
And what about the lady-in-waiting of New York City at the time?
而且呢當時這個紐約城的名願貴婦呢
Everyone heard his name
都聽到他的大名紛紛的
Come to him again and hope to be friends with him
又來找他希望跟他當朋友
And whenever there is a banquet
而且凡是有宴會啦
What's the classic? Wait.
有什麼雅籍啦等等
It's an honor to ask him to participate.
一定都要找他參加以為榮譽
Then Li Yucheng responded to everyone's warm hospitality
那麼李玉成為了回應大家熱情的這個招待
So he keeps making beautiful new clothes
所以他就不斷地做漂亮的新衣服
Maybe it's like the JC you see now
可能就像現在大家看到的JC
He makes all kinds of beautiful clothes
他做個更是各樣漂亮的衣服
So if he goes to several parties a day
那麼如果他一天要去好幾個party的話
he keeps changing clothes
他就會不斷地換衣服
Just like a bride coming out of a room
就好像新娘子出來一間客一樣
Every banquet needs to change into different clothes
每一個宴會都要換不一樣的衣服
And according to the record, his clothes are bright and colorful
而且根據記錄就是他的衣服都是鮮豔多目
Everyone who saw him thought he was a celestial being
看到他的人都以為是天上人
Appearing like a fairy
就好像是仙女一般的這樣出現
such a person
這樣的一個人
We probably don't imagine being an international student
我們大概不會想像是一個留學生
because in our today's terminology
因為我們今天的術語來說
We will say this is called public grievance
我們會說這個叫做民怨
This is called social grievance
這個叫做社交民怨
So
那麼
So what about his Kobe image?
所以他那個神戶的形象呢
I think it's a social
我覺得是一個社交
Including Celebrities Home Talented Women Writers
包括名人 家 才女作家
such an image
這樣的一個形象
We also think he looks like a phobia
我們也覺得他好像是一隻恐雀一樣
he's been like this all his life
他一輩子都是這樣的
On the one hand, he pays great attention to his own image.
一方面對自己的形象非常的重視
like self-pity
猶如固隱自憐
but on the other hand
但是另外一方面
We know his life is after the middle eye
我們知道他的人生在中眼之後
In fact, it is a Buddhist
其實是歸一佛教的
So he's on the one hand like a fear sparrow
所以他一方面像一隻恐雀一樣
admiring your own eyebrows
在欣賞自己的眉貌
In this respect, I am persistent in cultivating Buddhism.
這方面執著著要去修佛
To Hongfa
要弘伐
To promote the protection of animals
要宣揚保護動物
no killing etc.
不殺生等等的
figure of a giantess
一個女巨式的形象
Such a seemingly contradictory
這麼一個看似好像有一點矛盾
contradictory
彼此矛盾的
two self-identities
這樣的一個兩種自我認同
in his life
在他的生命裡面
from the beginning to the end
就是從一開始到最後
all the same
都是一樣的
Of course, Yu Sheng at this time
當然 余生這個時候
This luxury, this luxurious image
這種奢華這種豪奢的形象
In fact, it was with him at the time
其實是跟他當時所處的
Europe and the United States
歐美的時候
The environment has something to do with it
這環境是有一點有關係的
we'll talk about that later
這個我們就待會兒再談
Then, after Lu Mishen graduated from Columbia University,
那麼呂秘神從哥倫比亞大學之後
back to china
就回到了中國
Or is it presumably living a life of social prestige?
還是大概是過著社交名任的生活
But since 1926
但是從1926年開始
He also started to go to Europe and America alone
他也有開始獨自一個人到歐美去
live a long and vigorous life
過著一個長期有力的生活
Finally he went around and chose
最後他繞了一圈之後選擇
Live among the deep light and water colors of this Switzerland
住在這個瑞士的深光水色之間
Then he did not return to China until 1933
那麼一直到1933年他才回國
Then I lived in Beijing
那麼當時就住在了北京
But soon because of this
不過很快的因為這個
The outbreak of the war against Japan
這個對日戰爭的爆發
In order to avoid this action by the Japanese Tsinghua University
他為了要這個躲避日軍清華的這個行動
He went abroad again
他又再次的出國
Then I went through the wandering years again
那麼就又經歷了一番這個流離的歲月
So in the end he is in the state affairs of Hong Kong
那麼最後他是在這個香港國事的
Then let's say that the Republic of China starred in this
那麼我們說民國出演的這個
famous most famous traveler
著名的最著名的旅行的
What about civil travel?
民性的旅行呢
refers to this
指的就是這個
Lu Bicheng's work from 1926 to 1933
呂碧成在1926年到1933年的
The experience of this trip to Europe and America
這一趟歐美的這個遊歷的經驗
So why is this tour famous?
那麼這趟遊歷為什麼會有名呢
It wasn't that he was the only woman who went abroad
並不是當時只有他一個女人出國
It's because Lu Bicheng himself is famous
而是因為呂碧成他自己本來就很有名
right
對不對
Well, it's not because no one really went abroad at that time.
那麼也不是因為當時真的沒有別人出國
but because he himself went abroad while
而是因為他自己在出國的同時
He first announced in the newspaper that I was going abroad
他就先在報紙上面宣布了說我要出國了
And I'm going to be writing a post for dear readers
而且我將要為各位親愛的讀者寫郵寄
So this is almost like a self-promotional move.
所以這個他幾乎像是一個自我宣傳一樣的行動
He started traveling with himself
他就開始隨著他自己的旅行
In places like Suncheon Times in Beijing and Danyue Magazine in Shanghai
在北京的順天時報還有上海的淡月雜誌等等的地方
start serializing his post
開始連載他的郵寄
so in this way
那麼如此一來
The fame of this wit
這個女才子的名氣
And he was such a rare woman at the time
還有他當時畢竟是那麼稀少的一個女性
alone
獨自一個人
Not with family, not with personal friends, etc.
而不是跟著家人 不是跟著私友等等
Travel alone in Europe and America
獨自一個人去遊歷歐美
And it's a long-term self-help
而且還是長期的自助於行
such a legendary
這樣的一個傳奇性
plus his own fortune
再加上他自己的財氣
His writing is so talented
他的文筆 那麼的才華洋溢
plus newspapers and magazines
再加上報刊雜誌
flattery about the thing
對這件事情的吹捧
Synergy of various factors
種種的因素的會習
This makes Lu Bicheng's travel notes in Europe and America
使得這個呂碧成的歐美遊記
already popular at the time
在當時就已經大受歡迎
It is said that readers have strange expectations
據說讀者都是奇奇怪的盼望
I can see his travelogue
能夠看到他的遊記
Not only increased the number of his travel notes published
不但增加了他刊登遊記的
Sales of these newspapers and magazines
這些報刊雜誌的銷量
It even seems to have caused a lot of piracy
甚至好像還引起了不少的盜版
just steal his work
就是偷他的作品
He obviously didn't submit to this publication
他明明沒有投到這個刊物上面
This publication put his work on it
這個刊物卻把他的作品登在上面
Then said he voted
然後說是他投的
or even worse
或是甚至還有更惡劣的
just to steal his work
就是把他的作品偷天換日
Plus a lot of my own material
再加上了很多自己的材料
then say this
然後就說這個事
It's Lu Bicheng's
是呂碧成的
or
或者是说
It's obviously Lu Bicheng's name changed
明明是呂碧成的换了个名字说
this was written by someone else
这个是别人写的
various behaviors
种种不一的行为
So what about Lu Bicheng?
那么这个呂碧成呢
has been very harshly criticized
曾经非常严厉批评说
This is now this China this
这个现在这个中国这个
What about the behavior of the newspaper and magazine industry?
报中杂志界的这个行径呢
It's even scarier than this bandit
简直就是比这个强盗还要可怕
What about Lu Bicheng's mail?
那么呂碧成的邮寄呢
This is his Lu post from 1926 to 1933
这个他的呂邮是从1926到1933
But what?
不过呢
time this mailing was written
这本邮寄写作的时间
time of recording
记录的时间
Around 1926 to 1930
大概是1926到1930
then what
那么后来呢
pamphlet
就出了单行本
this is us today
这就是我们今天
This difficult postage route to Europe and America that will be discussed later
待会会谈的这个欧美难邮路
Then he has another name?
那么他还有另外一个名字呢
Red Snow Dollar
叫做红雪英元
so sorry
那么对不起
Of course, what about the name in front of it?
当然这个前面这个名字呢
It's more realistic
就是比较写实了
Because he just went to Europe and the United States to separate
因为他就是到欧洲跟美国去游离
What about the name Hongxue Yingyuan in the back?
后面这个名字红雪英元呢
It is entrusted to this Lu Bicheng
就是寄托了这个呂碧成
some feelings of my own life
自己的人生的一些感怀了
Then Lu Bicheng he from
那么呂碧成他从
Started writing in 1926
1926年開始寫作
And publish Europe and America roaming record
而且發表歐美漫遊錄
what is the type of his writing
他的寫作的類型是什麼呢
or classical Chinese
還是文言
He still writes in classical Chinese
他仍就用文言寫作
In fact, Lu Bicheng
事實上呂畢成一輩子
He never gave up classical Chinese
他從來就沒有放棄過文言
in the form of classical poetry
還有古典詩詞的形式
Then we know that he is a very important poetess in modern times
那麼我們知道他是近代非常重要的女詞人
Some people say that he is three hundred years old
有人說他是三百年來
The most important and last female poetess
最重要也是最後的一個女詞人
But this is already in 1926
但是這個已經是到了1926年
30 years
30年
We all know what kind of times this is
我們都知道這是什麼樣的時代呢
This is already the era of vernacular people learning, right?
這早就已經是白話人學的時代了吧
Didn’t the May Fourth News Movement happen in 1919?
五四新聞運動在1919年不就發生了嗎
Didn't the vernacular movement start a long time ago?
白話人的運動不是早就開始了嗎
May Fourth novel that shouted not as early as 1923
五四的小說那喊不是早在1923年
already published?
就已經出版了嗎
Peng Hong was published in 1926
彭宏就是在1926年出版的
And two years later, in 1928,
而在過兩年1928年的時候
Hu Shi's vernacular
胡適的白話
The first volume of literary history is about to appear
文學史的上卷也就要出現了
so it's a vernacular
所以這真是一個白話
an era of rising
崛起的一個時代
but
但是呢
Lu Bicheng seems to be completely ignoring the trend of this era
呂碧成他卻好像完全無視於這時代的潮流
He still insists on writing in classical Chinese
他仍然堅持要用文言來寫作
He still has to write poems in the old style
他仍然要寫舊體的詩
old style words
舊體的詞
And what?
而且呢
in his text
他的文字裡面
It's still such an allusion
仍就是那麼的耗用典故
I like beautifully crafted words
喜歡雕琢的華美的文詞
Then we can't help but ask
那我們就不禁要問
why one so
為什麼一個這麼
seems to be very progressive
好像很進步的
very independent
很獨立的
will be bold
會大著膽子
A person who went to Europe and America to roam for a long time by himself
自己一個人跑到歐美去長期漫遊的一個
advanced women
先進的女性
Then his literary creation
那麼他在文學的創作上
or at least in his stylistic choices
或至少在他文體的選擇上面
why would he
他為什麼會
seems so conservative
好像這麼保守
so old fashioned
這麼守舊
reluctance to accept new possibilities
不肯接受新的可能性
new trend
新的潮流
new things
新的事物呢
Is there any contradiction in this?
這中間有沒有矛盾呢
If
如果說
We feel that experiments in literary creation
我們覺得文學創作的實驗
itself seems to be a kind of exodus
本身也好像是一種出走
a kind of travel
一種旅行
an expedition
一個探險
a try
一種嘗試
a faraway word
一種遠行的話
then on behavior
那麼在行為上面
Willing to boldly go to Europe and America
願意大膽的去歐美
Lu Bicheng
去闖蕩的呂碧城
Why in the creation of his text
為什麼在他的文字的創作上
He never tried to go out and see
他就從來不肯試著走出去看看呢
That's what I'm curious about too.
那這個也是我會覺得好奇的問題
what about us for now
那麼我們暫時呢
Put this Lu Bi city aside
把這個呂碧城隔在一邊
Leaving the 1920s for a while
暫時離開1920年代
Then I want to share with you for a while
那麼我想暫時跟大家
Let's go back to the women of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
一起回到明清時期的女性
Of course for us women today
當然對我們今天的女性來說
Travel is a long way
旅行是一種長太樓
a long history
長長發生的事情
in my friends
在我的朋友裡面
will go on a self-guided trip
會出去自助旅行的
Of course I haven't done statistics.
我當然沒有做過統計啦
But I don't think it's good for women
不過我覺得搞不好女性
more than men
比男性還要多
But we often seem to feel
但是我們似乎常常覺得
travel alone
獨立一個人去旅行
This is a constitutional fight woman
這是一個憲斗女性
have the right
才有的權利
Because we always hear that women used to stay out of the house
因為我們總是聽說以前的女性是大門不出
Not bad for two
二門不賴的嘛
but actually
但是其實呢
Even if we go back to the Ming and Qing Dynasties
就算是回到明清時期
There are still many benefits
利害的情況還是很多的
There are still cases where women go out
女性出門的情形還是有的
For example a female she can follow her father
比方說女性她可以跟隨父親
The husband or even the son has gone to be an official somewhere else
丈夫或者甚至是兒子到其他的地方去當官了
When her husband became an official, she followed her, etc.
丈夫當官她就跟著去了等等
This is called phantom
這個叫幻遊
Or if the person she's marrying lives far away
或者是如果她結婚的對象住在很遠的地方
Doesn't she have to go through a long and slow road before she can get married?
那她豈不是先要經過慢慢長路才能夠出嫁
this is a distant marriage
這個是遠嫁
Then when she got married
那麼當她結了婚之後
if she's going home to save time
如果她要回家省期
feelings this may need you too
感情這也可能需要你
even in some special cases
甚至在某一些特殊的情況裡面
she may live for
她有可能為了生活
In order to maintain one's own livelihood
為了維持自己的生計起見
and have to go to different places to teach
而必須到不同的地方去教書
Teach other people's children teach your students
教別人家的孩子教你學生
This is the so-called belonging poem
這個就是所謂的歸屬詩
What about an example like this?
這樣子的例子呢
Of course, there were many during the Ming and Qing Dynasties
當然在明清時期是很多的
there are even more unfortunate things
甚至還有更不幸的事情
For example, if there is a war
比方說如果碰到戰亂了
Isn't that to escape?
那豈不是要逃亂嗎
In fact, escape is also a kind of travel
其實逃亂也是一種旅行
of course
當然呢
We have a situation similar to our so-called tourism today.
我們有比較類似我們今天這種所謂旅遊這樣的情況
that's still there
那也還是有的
if not
如果沒有的話
We would not be in the Ming and Qing travel poetry groups
我們就不會在明清旅行的詩文集體內
see those sights
看到那些觀賞風景
Seeing the monuments and sending out feelings and so on works like this
看到古蹟發出感懷等等這樣的作品了
And if we talk about the comparison below the middle level
還有如果談到比較中層以下
words from lower class women
下層階級的婦女的話
Their activities will also include such activities as entering the incense group
他們的活動裡面還會包括進香團這樣的活動
So in fact during the Ming and Qing Dynasties
所以事實上在明清時期
Women can still go out
女性還是可以出門行的
But today we will take one of them as an example.
不過今天我們就舉其中的一種例子來看看好了
in light this
在清淡的這個
There is a very famous literati in the world
我擎弄人間有一個非常有名的文人
Yuan Mei
叫做袁梅
That's more than eighteen people
就是十八十幾個人
This man certainly has all kinds of achievements.
這個人呢他當然有各式各樣的這個成就啦
but one thing
不過其中有一點呢
has always been the rear wheel
一直為後輪所
last until
撐到
or comparable
或者是比擬的
is that he has a habit
就是他有一個習慣
I just love accepting female disciples
就是很愛收女弟子
I love hanging out with female students
很愛跟女學生混在一起
After he stops being an official, of course he will be freer.
當他不做官了以後呢當然就更自由了
He lives in this random
他住在這個這個隨緣裡面
He will go to various places, such as Hangzhou and Suzhou
他會到各地去比如說杭州啦蘇州啦
Changshu, Songjiang, Zhengjiang, these places
長淑啦 松江啦 鄭江啊這些地方
Everywhere he goes
他每到一些地方呢
Those ones
那些
recruited his name
募了他的大名的
this
這個
The female students will come to him
女學生呢就會跑來找他
to worship him as master
要拜他做師父
He will be very happy to say that they are apprentices
他一定都會很歡喜的說他們做徒弟
What about Yuan Mei? For these female disciples, this Chunyu is beautiful and very helpful to them.
這個袁梅呢對這些女弟子呢是這個春玉有佳而且非常的幫忙他們
finally
最後呢
He also changed a book for his female disciples called
還為他的女弟子變了一本籍子叫做
The female disciple who followed the fate lost the election
隨緣女弟子失選
Of course they are not from the same place
他們當然並不是同一個地方的人
I just mentioned a lot of place names
我剛才提到好多個地名
Although they are all in Jiangnan
雖然都是在江南
These female disciples are actually scattered in different places
這些女弟子其實是散居在不同的地方的
But they will make an appointment with the original media teacher to meet in Hangzhou
但是他們會跟原媒老師約在杭州見面
They made an appointment to go to Hangzhou from various places
他們約好了從各個地方到杭州
Gather together at West Lake
一起在西湖聚會
And imitate male literati
而且模仿男性的文人
Gather together in the form of West Lake elegant books to mention poems and sing
西湖雅籍的形式聚在一起提詩營唱
Then also solid professional people
然後還固情專業的人
Help them draw a picture of the situation they are dealing with
幫他們把應付的情況給畫下來
For example, you can see
比方說各位可以看到
which one to press
這是要按哪一個
can you see an old man here
在這裡可以看到一個老頭子嗎
This should be the original medium
這應該畫的就是原媒
Then there are other women partying upstairs in West Lake
然後有其他的女性在西湖的樓上跟人一起聚會
They later called this saying "Hu Lou Asking for Karma"
他們後來就把這個話叫做胡樓請業圖
The poems they made at that time are also included in this collection
當時他們所做的詩也都留在這個集字裡面
we can still see
我們到現在都還可以看到
Of course examples like this are definitely not everyday
當然像這樣的例子絕對不是日常生活
It's not something that can happen every few days
不是一個三天兩頭就可以發生的事情
But this example still shows
但是這個例子仍舊顯示
At that time, it was still possible for women of the home class to travel
當時的歸宿階級的女性要出門旅行還是有可能的
In future generations, we are often subject to what we just said just now.
後世我們往往受到剛才所說的大門不出
The effects of aging on the two sides
二門不脈的老化的影響
I thought this woman must never go out
以為這個女人絕對不能出門
It is a historical reality that is released from all over the world and accepted
是放出四海而接準的一個歷史的現實
But actually I think this is not quite accurate
但是其實我覺得這個是不盡準確的
Although the saying that Chinese women never travel is not very accurate
雖然中國女性從來不旅行這句話不是很精確
But at the level of discourse
但是在論述的層次上面
women have to walk out
女性有行走出去
It is indeed a heart-to-heart exchange
確實是一個讓人心裡交流
one thing
一件事情
we know popular literature
我們知道通俗文學
often best performing
往往最能夠表現
Some issues that people really care about
人們心裡真正關心的一些問題
or a topic of interest
或者是覺得有興趣的話題
then we might as well
那麼我們也許就不妨
Give some examples from popular literature
舉一些通俗文學的例子來看看
Vice President Wang just introduced
剛才王副曾經介紹到
my first in this field of study
我的第一個這個研究領域
women's literature of the Ming and Qing Dynasties
是明清的女性文學
Especially one created by women
特別是女性所創作的一種
Novels with Yuwen titles
譽文題的小說
Then it's called Tanci novel
那麼叫做譚詞小說
let me talk for a minute
我稍微用一分鐘來講一下
what's the word
譚詞是什麼呢
Tanci is originally a kind of musicality
譚詞本來是一種音樂性
very nice
非常好聽的
a rap literature
一種說唱文學
this performer
這個表演者
One side is about to bounce
一面就是要彈著
Sanxian
三弦
or this person
或者是這個人
Pipa is in the lower left corner
琵琶在左下角
rap and sing at the same time
一面用說唱並用的方式
to tell long stories
來講述長篇的故事
then this is in
那麼這個在
Jiangnan area is a kind of
江南地區那是一種
very popular show
非常受到歡迎的表演
especially popular with women
尤其是受到女性的歡迎
Then it was intentional at that time
那麼當時呢就有意
some women who can read world characters
一些能夠讀書世字的女性
They took advantage of this particular form
他們就利用了這個特殊的形式
to create a dark-headed
來創作了一種暗頭式的
Can't really use it for performance
不能夠真的拿來表演
But you can watch it on your desk
但是可以放在書桌上面來看的
fiction for reading
專攻閱讀的小說
that's what i call this sting novel
那就是我所說的這個談刺小說
So as you can see in the upper left corner
那麼像各位在左上角看到的
This is a creation left over from the late Qing Dynasty
這個是一個清末的留下來的一個創作
Then you can see in the upper right corner
那麼右上角可以看看
How much time has this woman spent in her life
這個女人一輩子花了多少的時間
It's really a lifetime to write a novel
真的是一輩子來寫一部小說
This is their family heirloom handbook
這個是他們家傳的這個手插本
So what about stabbing novels?
那麼談刺小說呢
It basically uses the text to
它基本上是用運文來
Narrative in seven fonts
七字體的運文來敘事的
So it's above the form
所以它在形式上面
Certainly different from what we're used to
當然不同於我們所習慣的這個
Zhang Hui's novels in prose
散文的張輝小說
It's like pulling a kettle in the Three Kingdoms
像是三國拉水壺啦
Journey to the West La Red Mansion these novels
西遊拉紅樓啦這些小說
but
但是呢
Talking about stabbing novels also has Zhang Hui
談刺小說一樣是有張輝的
The same tells the full story
一樣是講述完整的故事的
Designs with characters and plots, etc.
一樣有人物有情節的設計等等
so i think it's
所以我覺得它是
In fact a novel
事實上還是一種長篇小說
So
那麼
What about the talk novel written by this female department?
這個女系所創作的這個談詞小說呢
a large percentage
有很大的比例呢
are telling a repeating story
都在講述一個重複的故事
Then change from this tone
然後再從這個基調上面去加以變化
what is this repeating story
這個重複的故事是什麼呢
That's what makes this story happen
那就是為了要讓這個故事發生啊
The heroines in the little book must leave his specifications
小書裡面的女主人翁都一定要離開他的規格
He's been staying home so there's no story
他一直待在家裡就沒有故事了
he must leave home
他一定要離開家
then to the public world
那麼要走向公眾的世界
so what to do
那麼怎麼辦呢
They must first dress up as men
他們一定要先扮成男子
they tie up their hair
他們要把頭髮束起來
to cover this piercing
要把這個耳洞遮起來
to cover the little feet
要把小腳遮掩起來
put on men's boots
要穿上男人的靴子
Then Mai Kaibuzi went out
然後麥開布子走出去
where are you going
走到哪裡去呢
to the center of power
走到權力的中心區
where is that
那是哪裡呢
must be capital city
一定都是京城
because they want to fulfill their dreams
因為他們要完成他們的夢想
You must first obtain citizenship
一定都先必須要考取公民
So these languages ​​are as exceptional
所以這些語言一如例外的
Their destination is the center of power
他們的目的地都是這個權力的中心
In Shenzhen, Meng Qianjun is like this. The female companion in men's clothes travels all the way from Yunnan to Beijing to take the exam.
在深圳裡面,孟茜君就是這樣女伴男裝遠從雲南一路到北京去參加考試
For the heroines in such novels, their travels actually herald very drastic changes in their lives
在這樣的小說裡面的女英雄,他們的旅行其實是預告了他們的生命會發生非常劇烈的變化
They will play roles that only men in society should play for a long time
他們會長期的去扮演社會上本來只有男性才要扮演的角色
That is to be an official, a general, a parent, a husband, etc.
那就是當官啦,當將軍啦,當家長啦,當丈夫啦,等等這些角色
And on their psychological level, these heroines hope that such a trip can go on forever
而且在他們的心理的層面上面,這些女英雄都希望這樣一趟旅行是可以永遠的繼續下去
so their travel has a big change
所以他們的旅行是有一個很大的改變
Well, of course, with our travel set, we also hope to increase their travel
那麼,當然以我們的旅行的這一套旅行,我們也希望能夠讓他們的旅行,能夠讓他們的旅行去增加
that, of course, on their psychological level, these heroines hope that such a trip can go on forever
那,當然,在他們的心理的層面上面,這些女英雄都希望這樣的一趟旅行是可以永遠的繼續下去
They will never need to go back to the norm to play the role of women in traditional society
他們永遠都不需要回到規格再去扮演傳統社會的女性的角色
chips their journey never has to end
chips their旅程永遠都不必到達終點
The way we see it today, we can easily
我們今天的眼光來看 我們可以非常輕鬆
It is easy to criticize these women writers
很輕易的去批評這些女作家
and the heroines they created
以及他們所創造的女英雄
Because they're just daydreaming, right?
因為他們只不過是在做白日夢而已 對嗎
They never thought about resisting the system of traditional society
他們根本就沒有想過要去抵抗傳統社會的體制
Never really reflect on gender roles
從來沒有真正反省性別 角色
Is it so fixed or not?
這麼固定到底是對還是不對
Because these heroines they just want to be men
因為這些女英雄他們只不過想變成男人而已
They didn't think about why the genders have such a division of labor
他們並沒有想過為什麼性別是要這樣的分工的
Is such criticism justified?
這樣的批評有沒有道理呢
Of course it makes sense, indeed.
當然是有道理的 的確如此
but i also want to ask
但是我也要問
The women in these novels run away, the imagination of going out
在這些小說裡面的女人的出走 走出去的想像
Doesn't it represent a very deep spirit of pursuit?
難道不代表一種非常深沉的追尋的精神嗎
Isn’t this a person worthy of our understanding today?
難道這就不是一個值得我們今天人就去體諒 了解
And a will to respect
而且尊重的一種意志嗎
And not precisely because women so long ago
而且不正是因為在這麼久以前的女性
a desire to have such an extreme pursuit
就具有這麼極竊的追求的一種慾望
So after hundreds or hundreds of years to stimulate a new generation of women
所以在數百年或百年後去刺激了新一代的女性
For example, a woman like Lu Bicheng goes out
比如說像呂碧成這樣的女人去走出去
Then I think it is because of the novel about death written by Li Shiling
那麼我想也就是因為李適伶創作的談死小說裡面
This exodus and this longing, this soul that seeks
這種出走還有追尋的這個渴望這個靈魂
expressed so strongly
表達的是這麼的強烈
So even in the novels about death written by Li Shi
所以呢 即使是同樣由李適所創作的談死小說裡面
There are also works that directly face the desire to go out and go out
也有的作品是去直接去面對這種跑出去走出去的慾望
the possible danger
所可能帶來的危險性的
Let's take a female work as an example
我們先舉一個女性的作品為例
This work is Heaven and Flowers
這個作品是天與花
The background of this talk about death is at the end of the Ming Dynasty
這個談死的背景是在明朝的末年
Then the plot of this novel is combined with the historical events of the last years of the Ming Dynasty
那麼這個小說的情節是結合了明朝末年的史事
A family story with this
跟這個一個家族的故事
Then the plot is very rich
那麼情節是非常豐富的
Of course it is impossible to explain to you here
當然不可能在這邊跟各位說明
But there is a very special place in this novel
不過這個小說裡面有一個很特殊的地方
It's that he keeps referring to women's going out
就是他不斷地去指涉到女性的出外
get out of this thing
走出去的這件事情
we have just said
我們剛才已經說過
in the novel
在小說裡面
If these hostesses don't leave the house
如果這些女主人都不離開家門的話
then there might be no story to tell
那就可能會沒有故事可以講
But Tianyuhua is special
可是天語花比較特別
Their heroine is at home
他們的女英雄是在家裡面
You can be a heroine without going out
就可以做女英雄 是不出門的
And the whole thing wants to say
而且整部想說
repeatedly warns his readers
一再地就在警告他的讀者
The danger of this woman going out
這個女人出門的危險性
There is a male protagonist in this novel
這個小說裡面有一個男性的主人翁
Zuo Weiming
叫做左維銘
Not Du Weiming Zuo Weiming
不是杜維銘 左維銘
But he is a great Confucian hero
但是他是一個儒家式的大英雄
Today's Great Hero
今天偉地的大英雄
He's pretty solid that women can't go out
他就非常堅實女性是不能夠外出的
let's see what he said
我們來看看他說的話
This is Mr. Zuo Weiming Zuo
這個是左維銘左先生
he was a teenager himself
他自己還是一個少年
When I was not married and still a single man
沒有結婚還是一個Single man的時候
He ran to a consummation room by himself
他自己跑到一個圓房
Tour in the garden
在園林裡面去游覽
what about this time
這個時候呢
he accidentally
他無意中呢
Met a girl who looks like a fairy
貼見了一個貌似天仙的女孩子
And he heard the
而且他打聽到了這位
This lady's name is Ring Green Turtle
這位女士的名字叫做環青龜
You can know it with a turtle
用一個龜字就知道
should be in the tortoise
是應該要身處在龜格當中的
He went to see Miss Ring Green Turtle?
他去看到這個環青龜小姐呢
with his family
跟著他的家人呢
Also play in the garden
也在園林裡面遊玩
So Zuo Weiming thought in his heart
於是左衛明就心裡就想了
This green turtle
這環青龜啊
Needless to say, talent and appearance
才貌自不必說啊
He is still the only one in the world
他還是世間無兩吧
but just
但只是
he is a lady fairy
他是一個仙精小姐
Then he should stick to the door
那貌他就應該緊守歸門呢
Should I steal my identity?
應該要偷藏身格嘛
How can I play outside with my mother?
怎麼可以隨著母親在外面玩耍呢
he went to peek by himself
他自己去偷看了
How about a young and beautiful girl?
人家青春美貌的少女呢
But I scold him in my heart
但是心裡面卻罵他
can't come out
不可以出來來
good
好
So
那麼
and after
後來呢
this
這個
once
有一次
he is on his way
他在自己在路途當中
he met his friend
他碰見了他的朋友
this friend is a couple
這朋友是一對夫妻
what about the husband
這個丈夫呢
because
因為
At the request of my wife, I brought my wife out
太太的要求於是就帶了太太出來
Where do you go to burn incense when you go out?
出門要去燒香去什麼地方
go on a pilgrimage to the mountain
山上去朝聖去
He was robbed by bandits on the way
在半途上就被盜匪搶劫了
Of course this beautiful lady almost lost her virginity
當然這個漂亮的太太差一點就失身了
Fortunately, the great hero Zuo Weiming saved them
還好大英雄左維銘就救了他們
This is Zuo Ming's conclusion after saving them
救了他們之後左銘下的結論就是這樣
Not what he considers his male friend
並不是他認為他的男性的朋友
It's very embarrassing not being able to protect my wife
沒有能力保護太太非常的丟臉
his conclusion is
他的結論是
It can be seen that Guiren can only be done in Guizhong
可見歸人只可在歸中做
Can he go out in person?
其可親身出外行呢
look at
你看看
It's because you're running out
就是因為你自己要跑出來
So today was hit by such a fire
所以今天遭到了這樣的大火
you almost died
你差一點就死定了
You almost ended up in this pack of wolves and tigers
你差點就現在這個狼虎堆中
There is no guarantee of the needle knot
就有針節不保了
this is his conclusion
這是他的結論
because or
因為或者
this
這個
Later he got married
後來他結婚了之後
Miss Huang Qinghui who was criticized by him just now
剛才的那位被他批評的黃清輝小姐
later became his wife
後來就變成了他的太太
then after marriage
那麼結婚之後
The unfortunate Miss Huang said
這個不幸的黃小姐就說
I want to go home in two days
過兩天我想回家
My mother said she would take me there
我媽說要帶我去
which garden to play
去哪個花園去玩
So this Zuo Weiming was furious
於是這個左維銘就大怒
just tell him
就跟他說
This is something that doesn't exist in our house
這個在我們家是沒有的事情
Talking about mountains and playing with water is a man's business
言山玩水這種事情是男人的事情
definitely not something women do
絕對不是女人做的事情
That one can go outside
那家其可外邊行
our family for generations
我們全家世世代代
No one has ever done such a shameful thing
從來沒有人做這麼丟臉的事
This is Zuo Weiming in Tian and Hua
這個就是天與花裡面左維銘
He represents a spirit of this novel
他代表這個小說的一個精神
one he showed
他所表現出來的一個
Restricting movement of women going out
限制女性出外的行動的
an idea
一種想法
and more interestingly
而且更有趣的是
This Zuo Weiming
這個左維銘
Not only does he have to take care of his wife
他不但要管自己的太太
Of course he wants to take care of his daughter
他當然要管他的女兒囉
Not only can his daughter not go out
他的女兒不但不可以出門
to explore the garden outside
到外面的花園去遊覽
I can't even go to my own back garden.
連自己家的後花園都不能去
Why can't you go to your own back garden?
為什麼自己家的後花園不能去呢
Of course you can imagine
當然各位可以想像
How did the story of Wu Dantian happen?
武丹田的故事又是怎麼發生的呢
The back garden is a very dangerous place
後花園是一個非常危險的地方
In fact, when his own daughter
事實上當他自己家的女兒
by order of the father
被父親的命令的通
A lot of things went to the back garden
很多的跑到了後花園去的事
It's true that something unfortunate happened
也的確發生了不幸的事情
Because they met the flower spirit tree monster in the garden
因為他們就遇到了花園裡面的花精樹怪
want to rape them, seduce them
想要來侵犯他們 引誘他們
Luckily his big baby is very heroic
當然還好他的大嬰兒非常英勇
As soon as I saw it, I got rid of these golden monsters in the garden
就一見就把這些花園的金怪給解決了
But the question is why is the novel written like this?
可是問題是小說為什麼要這樣寫呢
when i am alone
在我獨來
this garden is a special place
這個花園是一個特別的地方
The garden was originally a specification within a home
花園本來就是一個家內的規格
An end point with the outside world
跟外面的世界的一個終界點
is a very vaguely defined place
是一個定義非常模糊的地方
in this story
在這個故事裡面
The garden is a place that is about to run out
花園這個快要跑出去的地方
In fact, it means that the woman wants to poke her head out.
其實也就代表了那個女性想要探出頭去
That deep desire to go outside
想要往外走的那個很深沉的慾望
only in the novel
只不過在小說裡面
This woman's desire is suppressed
這個女性的慾望是被壓抑下來
was beheaded
是被斬絕的
I think if you look at it this way
我覺得這樣看的話
The sky and the flowers are actually from the back
天與花其實是從背面
It expresses the heart of women running away and pursuing
表達了女性出走跟追尋的一個內心
"Star World"
《明星世界》
women's novels write about their education
女人的小說這麼寫他們的教育
What about the man?
那男人呢?
Let's take another example of a male work
我們再舉一個男性的作品的例子
There is a very special novel in the early Qing Dynasty
清朝初年有一部很特別的小說
It's called "The Biography of Acting English"
叫做《行事英文傳》
You know this is a talk
各位知道這是一個講
Very Scary Story of Father Han
非常可怕的漢父的故事
The Novel's Travels to Women
小說對女性的出門旅行
made a very special description
做了非常特別的描寫
A scholar once analyzed for us
有一位學者曾經為我們分析過
The heroine in "The Biography of Acting in English"
在《行事英文傳》裡面的女主角
It's Han's father named Xue Sujie
就是漢父叫薛素姐
He went out four times in his life
他一輩子有四次出門
The experience of traveling to distant places
去比較遠的地方旅行的經歷
The first time was to go to Mount Tai to burn incense
第一次是去上泰山去燒香
second time to beijing
第二次去北京
The third time to Huai'an
第三次去淮安
The fourth time to go to Chengdu
第四次去成都
The next three times are to go
後面三次都是去
In order to find his drunk driving husband
為了去找他酒駕不歸的丈夫
good
好
So
那麼
Then this scholar mentioned that
那麼這位學者他就提到說
in the biographies of entertainers
在行事藝人傳裡面
The male author will constantly question
這個男性的作者會不斷的質疑
And mocking a woman's ability to take care of herself outside
而且嘲笑女人在外面照顧自己的能力
want to cut vegetarian sister
想削素姊
Even if he walks the avenue at home
即使他在家裡面橫行大道
make the husband kneel at his feet
讓丈夫跪在他的腳邊
but as soon as you go out
但是只要一出門
he is a helpless man
他就是一個無助的人
So let's take a look at this Miao Xian
那麼我們來看看這個苗顯
This is the 73rd chapter I want to talk about
這個是想說的第73回
It's just talking about burning incense on Mount Tai
就是在講泰山燒香
You can take a look
各位可以看看
this small
這個小
Inside, there will be Miao Xian, who burns incense on Mount Tai.
裡面特別會就苗顯了泰山燒香的
this lively situation
這個熱鬧的情況
This is the Jade Emperor Biography Meeting on March 3
這是3月3日玉皇傳會
Then this Mount Tai is full of people
那麼這個泰山上面是人山人海的
impenetrable
勇己不透的
and what is this dangerous
而且這個危險的是什麼
mixed sex in this place
在這種地方是男女混雜的
There is no way to say that males are on one side and females are on the other.
沒有辦法說男中一邊女中一邊
And it's not divided into two
而且還不分兩件
So regardless of gender
所以不管是性別
Or classes are all confused
或者是階級都是混淆的
such a situation
這樣的情況
Only those public officials who take risks
只有那些有所好險的公貫
And those countless wives
還有那些無居無數的婆娘
Who will be innumerable
誰會無居無數呢
The wives are counted
婆娘都是有居有數的
countless wives
無居無數的婆娘
Just without a husband and without a home
就是沒丈夫的沒家的
bad women and so on
就是不良的婦女等等的
Then you will be paired and haunted
那麼才會結對出沒
There is no gentleman who is educated and reasonable
沒有那個知書達理的君子
Or the woman with the hand knot
或者是那個手結的婦人呢
will appear here
會出現在這裡的
Then he described below
然後下面他就形容
describe this woman woman
形容這個婦人 女人
Where is the danger in such a place?
到了這種地方的危險在哪裡
after this ridge number
這個山脊號之後
He said, these are the vagrants
他說呢這些就是浮浪子弟呢
Whenever you see a woman coming
只要看到有女人走過來
she wants ice cream without glasses
她不戴眼睛要吃冰淇淋
pointing
手裡還要指
Then there are constant comments in the mouth
然後嘴巴裡還有不斷的評論
comment on what
評論什麼呢
commented that
評論說
Oh, this man's hair is so shiny.
哎呀這個人的頭梳的好亮啊
what about that person
那個人呢
Yo this foot is so small
呦這個腳好小啊
It's beautiful
成的真漂亮
Or that this person can't
或者是說這個人不行
too much powder
粉差太多了
face is pale
臉都泛白了
He also said that the oil was not enough.
又說那個油油使得不夠啊
this person is very dry
這個人非常乾燥
I said this mouth is too big
我就說這個嘴太大了
terrible eating too much
很可怕吃太多
Well, this ass is too big, right?
那個呢這個屁股也太大了吧
Didn't get up to do anything?
都沒起來做事吧
Wait, you are constantly criticizing
等等就是不斷的在批評呢
women on the road
路上的這些女性
what about these women
那這些女性呢
even if they are together
即使她們也是團體的在一起
but they
但是她們
completely incapable of protecting oneself
完全沒有任何保護自己的能力
Then I won't quote
那麼下面我就不引了
because at the end of this episode
因為這一段情節的最後
It's actually a very dire situation
其實是一個非常慘烈的狀況
That means
那就是說
A bunch of wealthy people centered on Shasujie
削素以削素解為中心的一堆富裕
When passing by this group of floating children
在經過了這一批浮浪子弟的跟前的時候
because they said something wrong
他們因為一句話說得不對
Offended this group of bad boys
得罪了這群這個壞子弟
They came forward and not only called these women
他們就上前來不但把這些女人都打來
And stripped all their clothes
還把他們所有的人衣服都扒光了
These women
一句一句這些女人
The last is to be naked when going up this mountain
最後是在這個上山的時候是赤身漏體
It's like being insulted
等於說是受盡了侮辱
as the end of this episode
作為這段情節的結束
then it's clear
那麼很清楚的
what about this place
這個地方呢
What is manifested is
彰顯的是
A Danger of Women Walking Out of Homes and into Crowds
女性走出歸房走入人群的一種危險
Then of course it was that era
那麼當然也是那個時代
For this woman likes to burn incense
對於這個女人喜歡去燒香
pilgrimage
上香了朝聖
A Criticism of the Habit
這種習慣的一個批評
Then it is very obvious that
那麼這個非常明顯的是
A male author's warning for women traveling
男性作者對於女人旅行的警告
But whatever we just saw
不過呢 不管是我們剛才看到的
Lessons from Tianyuhua
天雨花裡面的教訓
or in the form of male authors here
或者是這裡男性作者的形式
This comparison game pen in English
英文狀裡面的這個比較遊戲之筆
He actually corresponds to
他對應的其實都是
Did women in society at that time really have a chance to step out of the house?
當時社會上的女人真的有機會走出家門嗎
They really have the opportunity to participate in the activities of the public
他們真的有機會參與公眾的活動
it's a reality
這是個現實
If it's not true because some women
如果不是真的因為有一些女性
I will go to public gardens to enjoy with my family
會到公共的園林裡面跟家人一起去遊賞
If it wasn't true some women would be in the Mirror Corps
如果不是真的有一些女性會參加鏡像團
Then these popular novels
那麼這些通俗小說
He doesn't have to express such great anxiety and resistance.
他也就不必去表達這麼大的焦慮跟反抗了
actually
其實
Whether these are real
不論是現實中這些
To deter women they go on a tour
威懾婦女他們去遊山玩水
Denmin filed
登民提起
or dissatisfaction
或者是失惠雅極
Or ordinary class women who go to temples to burn incense
或者是一般階級的婦女她去逛廟去燒香
or even
或甚至是
Female writers like Peng's novels are in the novels
像彭此小說的女作家在小說裡面
to imagine a woman
去想像一個女人
What kind of travel alone
什麼的萬里獨行
I think it shows
這些我想都表現出
Chinese women before modern times
在現代以前的中國女性
their timeless
他們那種跨越時代
A Common One Desire Across Regions
跨越地區的一種共同的一個渴望
that's the desire to get out
那就是走出去的渴望
destination of travel
旅行的目的地或者是旅行當中
What is there to see
到底有什麼見能
It seems that it is not the point
似乎反而不是重點了
The point is to be able to go beyond the original boundaries and limitations
重點就在於能夠跨越原來的界線跟限制
Of course, under the constraints of the social environment at that time
當然在當時的社會環境的限制下
Women's travel experience and women's imagination of travel
女性的旅行經驗跟女性的旅行的想像
It makes us feel that it is actually very precious.
都讓我們覺得其實是彌足珍貴的
Okay, so during the Ming and Qing Dynasties we used this
好 那麼明清時期我們就以這個
A few brief examples to introduce to you
簡短的幾個例子大概的跟各位介紹一下
Going further down, to the end of the Qing Dynasty and the beginning of the Ming Dynasty
再往下走呢 到了清末明初時期
Of course it's different
那當然就不一樣了
Women's travel opportunities in this era have increased a lot
這個時代的女性的旅行的機會就增加了很多
don't talk too much
別多不說
Just mentioned female students
剛才提到女學生
Sometimes there have been female students
有時候已經出現了女學生
She is going abroad to study
她要到外地去求學
even study abroad
甚至到外國去留學
if only
只要
It's very possible to go to school.
要去求學都非常可能其實
to lady
到女士
Of course we also remember
我們當然也還記得
Liu Bichang went to Tianjin for the first time
劉碧長第一次跑到天津去
just to study
就是為了要去求學
exist
在
When Qing Ruo
青若的時候
around the beginning of the twentieth century
差不多二十世紀初年的時候
We also finally saw
我們也終於看到了
first step
第一步
by dedicated women
是由專門女性
written by
所寫作的
foreign mail
外國的郵寄
wife of a diplomat
當時一位外交官夫人
Written by Shanshini
善氏尼所寫的
ghost hair travel post
鬼毛旅行寄
This is from 1903
這是1903年的
She later wrote another
她之後又寫了一部
It's called "Return to the Front" in 1910
叫做《歸前寄》是1910年
out
出的
the lady
這位女士
Goodness, she's actually
善氏尼她其實
her post is special
她的郵寄很特別
So the last ten years
所以最近就十年
received
受到了
considerable academic attention
相當多的富於時學界的注意
His husband is called Qin Xun
他的丈夫叫做秦循
Is a diplomat in the late Qing Dynasty
是晚清的一個外交官
went to many places to have accidents
到了很多的地方去出事
since 1889
從1889年開始
Shan Shilin followed his husband
善事林就跟著他的丈夫
Traveled to many places
到了非常多的地方去遊歷
Shan Shilin because he is a destination
善事林因為他是一個歸宿
He took what he had seen and heard
他就把他研圖所見所聞
And his thoughts were written and mailed
還有他的感想都寫成了郵寄
And he writes a big point of mailing
而且他寫郵寄的很大一個重點
It is to encourage women in China at that time to speak
就是要鼓勵當時中國的女性言
imitate his spirit
效法他的精神
Travel abroad to broaden your knowledge
出國遊歷來增廣見聞
These two parts mailed the previous part of Mandarin
這兩部郵寄前一部國語形記
It's about his experience in Japan and Russia
講的是他在日本跟俄國的見聞
The second part of Homecoming is basically about countries in Western Europe
第二部歸宿記講的基本上是西歐的國家
we have to pay special attention
我們要特別注意的
It is because of good deeds, Lin's historical environment, his career
就是因為善事林他所處的歷史環境事業
Wanqing is special
比較特別的是婉青
So he writes the post with a special perspective
所以他是用一個特別的視角來寫郵寄的
what kind of perspective
是什麼樣的視角呢
The first is that he is a woman
第一個就是他是一個女性
He is going with his peers
他是要跟他的同儕
Chinese woman speaking with dream
同夢的中國女性講話的
The second is that he is a Chinese woman
第二個就是他是中國的女性
The third point is
第三個重點就是
He is a woman in China who is being bullied by foreign powers
他是正在受列強欺劣的中國的女性
so you can see
所以各位可以看到
For example, he would say this in "He You Ji"
他在例如說他有記裡面會這樣講
He will say that our Chinese women are originally locked up
他會說我們中國的女性本來是個關起來的
So we never know the outside world
所以我們從來都不知道外面的世界
Because I don't know the outside world
因為不知道外面的世界
So we don't actually know ourselves
所以我們其實是不知道自己的
Because I have never seen foreign countries
因為沒看過外國
So I don't know ours is actually called China
所以我不知道我們這個其實叫中國
This is mutually defined
這個是彼此定義的
So he said that since I went to Japan
所以他說我自從去了日本之後
I see Japanese women are very patriotic
我看到日本的婦女都非常的愛國
So I was also inspired
所以我也受了啟發
I know we women need it too
我知道我們婦女也是需要
patriotic this is important to the country
愛國的這個對國家是重要的
Then I also spontaneously gave birth to patriotism
那麼我也由然的生出了愛國之心
which of course encourages his potential female readers
那這當然也是在鼓勵他的可能的女性的讀者
Even women should be governed by national concepts
就是女人也要由國家觀念
Well, this is a good deed that leaves blood
那麼這個是善事離血的這個
A more important main axis in the mail
郵寄裡面一個比較重要的一個主軸
Of course, he is also a woman who is full of knowledge.
那當然他也是一個還滿有見識的一個女性
I heard that Tolstoy was sent by him from China
這個聽說托爾斯泰是他去受到中國來的
So I haven't gone through a very strict inspection
所以我還沒有仔細經過很嚴格的考察
Do not know is not true
不知道是不是真的
But it is said
但是據說呢
He was the first person in China to mention
他是第一個在中國第一個人提到
This Russian writer Tolstoy's people
這個俄國的文豪托爾斯泰的人
OK
OK
good
好
However, this good deed is from him, although he is a woman who looks up to the original owner
不過呢這個善事離他雖然是一個高瞻原主的女性
but what do we have to say
但是呢我們必須說
He will basically still be classified by us as a home of the Qing Dynasty
他基本上還是會被我們歸類為一個清代的歸宿
How should I put it, he is still in
怎麼說呢他其實還是在
Continuing the oil change tradition we just mentioned
延續著我們剛才提到的那種換油的傳統
Why did he have the opportunity to travel abroad?
為什麼他會有機會到國外去遊歷呢
That's because he went abroad with his husband
那就是因為他跟著他的丈夫出國的
So he is a follower role
所以他是一個跟隨者的角色
He played the role of a wife in a family to go abroad
他是在一個家庭裡面扮演一個太太的角色來出國的
then maybe a little later
那麼或許在稍微晚一點
We have a character for comparison
我們有一個作為對比的人物
This figure may be even more legendary in terms of travel
這個人物可能在旅遊方面就更具有傳奇性了
who is this
這個是誰呢
This is Kang Youwei's second daughter
這個是康有為的二女兒
Kang Tongbi
叫做康同碧
Kang Tongbi is also a person from the end of the 19th century to the 20th century
康同碧同樣是19世紀末到20世紀的人
He is Kang Youwei's second daughter
他是康有為的二女兒
If you have read Zhang Yihe's The Last Noble
如果各位讀過張一和的最後的貴族的話
maybe remember
也許還記得
Because it actually mentioned in that book
因為那本書裡面其實提到過
Kang Tongbi in his later years and Kang Tongbi's daughter
晚年的康同碧還有康同碧的女兒
That Luo Yifeng
那个罗义凤
So what kind of legendary trip did he have?
那么他有一个什么样传奇性的旅行呢
That was in the spring of 1902
那就是在1902年的春天
Has the reform already failed?
当时早就已经变法失败了嘛
So that Kang Youwei has gone out of town
所以那个康有为呢已经跑到外地去了
to many places
到了很多地方
Finally, in 1902, Kang Youwei was here
最后呢1902年的时候呢他康有为是在这个
From Southeast Asia to India
在从南洋然后到了印度
Well, Kang Tongbi is not yet 20 years old at this time
那么康同毕呢这个时候呢还不到20岁
this is 19 years old
这个19岁
After he found out where his father was
他知道了父亲在什么地方之后呢
I decided to rush to accompany my father to take care of him.
就决定要赶去陪伴父亲照顾父亲
So it is said that he is wearing men's clothes
所以呢这个据说呢他是穿了男人的衣服
then alone
那么独自一个人
Go south from this Hexi Corridor
从这个河西走廊往南走
Then through Nanyang
那么经过了南洋
In the end he really went to India to accompany his father Kang Youwei
最后他真的到了印度去陪伴他的父亲康有为
So how do we know this?
那么这件事情我们怎么知道的呢
Because Liang Qichao used to be here
因为呢梁启超他曾经在这个
It was mentioned in Hidden Soldiers Relief
隐兵士释怀里面提到了这件事
Then he will talk about Kang Tong
那么他就讲说这个康同
Last year, a person went to India to torture
在去年是一個人跑到印度去刑侵
He is only 19 years old
他才19歲 是妙齡若職
This is actually a little bit sexist.
這個其實是稍微有一點性別歧視的
Young age is not necessarily good job
妙齡不一定若職
But he praised Kang Tongbi for being able to
但是他就稱讚康同弼是可以
Blind Tao Accounting for Thousands of Miles
零數千里之盲韜賬物
It's really rich and has no dogs
真是虎富無犬子也
The comparison between this young and professional and the rich but without dogs
這個妙齡若職跟虎富無犬子的對比
It's actually quite an interesting value judgment.
其實是相當有趣的一個價值判斷
After telling the story
在講述了這件事情之後
Liang Qichao also quoted two poems by Kang Tongbi
梁啟超還引用了康同弼的兩首詩
These are the two poems you see below
就是以下各位看到的這兩首詩
This is the word count of Kang Dongpil
這個是康同弼的字數
He said that social mountains and rivers are formed
他說社會山河立結成
A society is of course a social state
社會當然就是社會國
It was a place name in India at that time.
就是印度當時的一個地名
society city
社會城
That's where the Buddha preached the scriptures and preached the Dharma.
佛就是在那裡講經宣法的
Sanxun
不經壞店屬三尋
If you don't pass, you don't pass the temple
不經就是不經寺
It is also the place where the Buddha preached
同樣也是佛陀說法的地方
The tone below is very red
下面這個語氣就非常的紅大了
he said bad lady rare
他說 惡劣女士稀有者
I am the first person
我是之那第一人
it's very very confident
這是非常非常自信
very strong tone
非常堅強的語氣
Believe that you can do it
堅信自己是能夠這樣做到的
first chinese woman
第一個中國女人
Of course, these two poems both show a very gray and red momentum.
當然這兩首詩都展現了非常灰紅的氣勢
after this
在這個之後
Kang Tongbi became a wife again in 1903
1903年康同畢又成婦命
Actually went to America to study
其實到了美國去求學
Finally in 1909 when
最後在1909年的時候
from Columbia University
他從哥倫比亞大學的
He had no way of going to the real columbia at that time
那個時候他沒有辦法上真正的哥倫比亞大學
He can only go to women's college
他只能夠上女子學院
It's Bernard
就是Bernard
he graduated from there
他從那裡畢業了
He's actually a Colombian woman
他其實也是哥倫比亞的女子
Girls college's first graduate Asian student
女子學院的第一個畢業的亞洲的學生
This is Kang Tongbi's trip
這個是康同畢的旅行
Of course we have to say that Kang Tongbi has an extraordinary background
當然我們得說康同畢他的背景非凡
After all, he is Kang Youwei's daughter
他畢竟是康有為的女兒
his extraordinary family background
他的不平凡的家庭背景
In fact, it created his extraordinary experience
其實造就了他這不平凡的經歷
But his whole travel experience
不過他的整個的旅行經驗
Let's say he wants a man of his own volition
比方說他要一個人出於自己的意志
so far away
那麼遠
really thousands of miles away
真的是數千里之遙
India to save Qing
印度去省清
It is also from the kind of women I just mentioned
同樣是出於我剛才所提出來的那種女性的
the desire to get out
走出去的那種渴望
a will to seek
一種追尋的意志
in fact
事實上
Kang Tongbi and Lu Bicheng
康同畢跟呂畢成
They were all born in the 1880s
他們都是1880年代出生的
So they can be said to be peers
所以他們可以說是同輩人
Then they are also in the youthful temple age of life
那麼他們也同樣的都在人生的青春廟齡時期
did something special
做了特別的事情
Kang Tongbi traveled thousands of miles to India to save
康同畢他是萬里前往印度去省
Wake up and study abroad
醒青 然后出国留学
And Bi Chen is about the same age
而与碧晨却在差不多的年纪
Run away from home, go to Tianjin to explore the world
离家出走 到天津去闯天下
Their travels all started
他们的旅行都开创了
Some special experiences in their personal lives
他们个人生命的一些特殊的经验
They are also famous historical environments in the late Qing Dynasty
他们也都是清末名出的历史环境
create an environment for them
为他们创造了这样的一个环境
such an opportunity
这样的一个机会
Of course, the end of the Qing Dynasty also began to appear
当然 清末也开始出现了
more female students
更多的女留学生
They go far and wide to read
他们远复重扬去读书
including the heroines we are familiar with
包括我们所熟悉的女英雄
Qiu Jin is also around this time
邱锦 也是在差不多这个时候
Those who went abroad to study, those who went to Japan to study
出国去念书 到日本去念书的
so we can see
所以我们可以看到
from this time on
从这个时候开始
Chinese women have more and more opportunities to travel abroad
中国女性出国旅行的机会就越来越多了
so from here
那么从这里呢
we can finally go back
我们终于可以又回到
Al Bichen's body
铝碧晨的身上
And her trip to Europe and America
还有她的欧美之行
What about Al Bichen's trip?
铝碧晨的旅行呢
in a special historical context
是在一个特殊的历史情境
in the late 1920s
在1920年代後期
What about this period?
這個時期呢
What kind of period was it?
是怎麼樣的一個時期呢
For Lu Bicheng
對於呂碧城來說
His origin is China
他的出發地是中國
His destination is Europe and America
他的目的地是歐美
So the date in the 1920s
那麼1920年代這個日期
for China
對中國來說
For Europe and the United States
對歐美來說
different meanings
意義是不盡相同的
The year he set out was 1926
他出發的那一年是1926年
in China
在中國呢
what year was that
那是哪一年
it was 1930
那是1930年
in China
在中國呢
what year was that
那是哪一年呢
that's exactly
那正是
It was the year when the Beifa Movement started
正是北發運動開始的那一年
So
那麼
where he goes
他去的地方
where is his destination
他的目的地呢
In Europe and America?
在歐美呢
What about the 1920s?
1920年代呢
yes
是
Simply put, the 1920s were
簡單的說1920年代是
World War I
第一次世界大戰的
postwar period
戰後時期
Because the year of the European War
因為歐戰的年份呢是
1914 to 1918
1914年到1918年
then the 1920s
那麼1920年代
It was after the end of the European War in 1918
是就是1918年歐戰結束之後的
a special period
一段特殊的一個時期
Caught in the European War in the 1920s
20年代就夾在歐戰
Followed by the 1930s
跟後來30年代的
For example, during the Great Depression in the United States
比方說美國的大蕭條之中
So when it comes to the European War
那麼提到歐戰
We must say this World War I
我們必須說這個第一次世界大戰
Impact on the Western world
對於西方世界的影響
It's indescribably huge
之巨大是非常難以描述的
I myself have actually read
我自己以前其實讀了
Because I used to study in the Department of Chinese Literature
因為以前念國文系的關係
Actually read a lot of literature
其實讀了很多的文學作品
But I'm really late
但是我其實到很晚才
Only then did I really realize that there are so many things that are
才真正體會到有那麼多的東西是
Why is it so similar to World War I?
為什麼真的那麼跟第一次世界大戰
so relevant
那麼的相關
then
那麼當時呢
What about World War I?
第一次世界大戰呢
It's because of this twentieth-century advance in weapons
它因為這個二十世紀武器的進步
so amazing
太厲害了
So it caused this
所以它造成的這個
The casualties far exceed the casualty rate of wars that humans could have imagined before.
死傷的是遠遠超過以前人類能夠想像的戰爭的傷亡率
Moreover, the First World War also invented a very special method of warfare
而且呢 第一次世界大戰還發明了一個非常特殊的戰法
It's what you see in the picture
就是各位在圖片上看到的
This is Trench, the so-called Haogou Warfare
這個是Trench 就是所謂的豪溝戰
That is to say, the people on both sides have spent many months this year.
也就是雙方人馬都今年累月的
This year, I have been preparing for the battle in Haogou for many months.
今年累月的都在豪溝裡面去備戰
So for a very, very long time soldiers have to stay in this
所以非常非常長的時間軍人都要待在這個裡面
then they can't get out
那麼他們走不出去的
It's really stuck inside and can't get out
這真的是被困在裡面走不出去
Moreover, the sky you look up at is incomplete.
而且呢 往上看的天都是不完整的
Looking up, you can only see a thin line of sky above Haogou
抬頭看只能看到豪溝上面的一線之天而已
Even days are incomplete
連天都是不完整的
Then according to the conjecture of later generations?
那麼根據後人的這個揣想呢
a war experience like this
像這樣子的一個戰爭的經驗
For the psychology of the soldiers who participated in the war at that time
對於當時參加戰爭的戰士們的心理
had a very, very large impact
造成了非常非常大的影響
is a huge battle
是一個巨大戰
window pain
的窗痛
So
那麼
and therefore in this
也因此在這個
after the first event war
第一次事件大戰之後
we can almost say
我們幾乎可以說
too many important
太多太多的重要的
this western literary work
西方的這個文學作品
World War I
都跟第一次世界大戰
caused by the psychological
所造成的心理
Trauma is relevant
創傷是有關係的
I just give a few examples
我隨便舉幾個例子
Although this is already
雖然這個對我來說已經是
History learned a very long time ago
非常久遠以前學習的歷史了
but for example
但是呢比方說
This is probably the one we are most familiar with
這個我們可能大家最熟悉的
Elliott
英國的大師人艾劣特
T.S. Eliot
T.S. Eliot
Some of his most important works such as
他最重要的一些作品比方說
Wasteland
荒原的Wasteland
or this
或者是這個
What is the name Hollow Man or Hollow Man?
叫什麼空洞人還是空心人
The Hollow Man
The Hollow Man
It's all from the 1920s
都是20年代的作品
And it's all
而且呢都是
In response to this European war
回應到這個歐戰的
some spirit
一些精神
state
狀態
For example, this wasteland is supposed to be in 1922
比方說這個荒原是應該是1922年的
then this
那麼這個
Hollow Man's might be a little later
空心人的可能稍微晚一點
Another example is the American writer Hemingway
又比方說美國作家海明威
his battlefield dream
他的戰地春夢
Haruka battlefield is this
戰地春夢是這個
Affair to Arms
Affair to Arms
He is also talking about himself
他也是在講他自己
Some of the First World War
在第一次世界大戰當中的一些
this traumatic experience the sense of absurdity of war and more
這個創痛的經驗戰爭的荒謬感等等
That's 1929
那就是1929年的作品
These are all works from the 1920s
這些全部都是20年代的作品
what they responded to
他們所回應的
All from 1914 to 1918
都是這個1914到1918年的
this world war one
這個第一次世界大戰
then these works
那麼這些作品
they all have something in common
他們都有一些共同的基調
have some themes
有一些主題
they all acted
他們都表現了
the generation after the war in europe
在歐戰之後的那一代人
the psychological feeling
心理上面所感受到的那種
lost hopeless
失落 絕望
disillusioned disillusioned
破滅 幻滅
The collapse of this value
這個價值的崩潰
everything in the world is meaningless
世界一切都沒有意義的
such a state of mind
那樣的一個心理狀態
It's just like
就像是
This is what Elliot's Holloman said
這個是Elliot的Holloman裡面所說的
He just said we were empty
他就說我們是空的
there is nothing in us
我們裡面是沒有東西的
Even if there is something, it's just stuffed with straw
就算有東西也只是稻草塞著的
like a stuff animal
就像一個stuff animal一樣
It's stuffed there, it's stuck there
是塞在那裡的 撐在那裡的
There are straws in the head
腦袋裡面都是稻草
nothing
是什麼都沒有的
And what?
而且呢
It's just like
就像是
This tangible and intangible thing is the same
這個有形無體的東西一樣
I think this picture is very
我覺得這幅圖非常
for me
對我來說
Very meaningful expression of that feeling
非常有意味深長的表現了那種感覺
yes
是
like this floating shadow
就像是飄蕩的這個影子一樣
is colorless
是沒有顏色的
is powerless
是沒有力量的
You see it seems to be moving
你看到它好像在動吧
In fact, it has no power at all.
其實它根本就沒有力的
there is no motion
是沒有motion的
so finally
那麼最後呢
What about the end of this poem?
它這個詩的結尾呢
just say
就說
this is how the world ends
世界就是要這樣結束
This is the way the world ends
This is the way the world ends
Not with a band
Not with a band
I didn't even think about it
連碰得想一聲都沒有
how did this world end
這個世界是怎麼結束的呢
just use
只是用
softly
輕輕的一聲
Humper is a
Humper是個
Wu Ye or wrong gas
烏葉或者是錯氣
small sound
小小的一聲
no sense to end with a sound
沒有意義的一個聲音來結束的
this reminds me
這就讓我想到
From "Dragon Dream"
從《龍夢》裡面說
Yuan Xiaojie passed
原小潔過了
There is still a touch
都還有碰的一聲
nothing
才什麼都沒有呢
But in this wild world
可是呢在這個荒原的世界裡面
Even Yuan Xiaojie's swollen sound
連了原小潔發的那一聲泡脹的聲音
none
都是沒有的
So this is what the Western world calls
那麼這個就是西方世界所謂
A Portrayal of the Spirit of the Lost Generation
失落的一代的精神的寫照
This is the so-called spiritual wasteland
這個就是所謂的精神的荒原
This is the side on the window from the 1920s
這個是1920年代的窗上的那一面
but on the other hand
但是呢另一方面呢
What about America in the 1920s?
20年代的美國呢
It was a prosperous golden age
卻是一個繁華一順的黃金時代
What about other big cities in the western world?
那麼其他的西方世界的大城市呢
including London and Paris
包括像是倫敦啦 巴黎啦
And what about New York in the United States, and big cities like Chicago?
還有美國的這個紐約啦 芝加哥這些大城市呢
What they actually experienced was a
他們其實呢經歷的是一個
we call it crazy sales
我們叫做狂銷
Crazy
狂造的
era of frenzied sales
狂銷的時代的
It was a very noisy time
是一個非常吵鬧的一個時代
in this era
在這個時代
There are some social and cultural peculiarities in the 2000s
二零年代有一些社會文化的特殊性
For example, if we're going to talk about art
比方說如果我們要講藝術的話
It is an era of so-called Art Deco
它是一個所謂Art Deco的時代
Features of Art Deco
Art Deco的特色
For example, as you can see in the picture in the middle
就是比方說像各位看像中間的這個圖
there are many colors
是有很多的色彩的
There are many geometric lines
是有很多的幾何的線條的
influenced by industrial civilization
是受了工業文明的影響
So those more mechanical designs that appeared
所以出現的那些比較機械式的設計的
You can see it on the clothes
在服裝上面各位可以看到
The hat worn by the woman in the lower left corner
左下角這個女性戴的帽子
It's what you want to describe a woman as a smoker
就是你要形容女人的煙室妹形
This is the smoke room girl
這個就是煙室妹形
It's also the age of movies
同時它也是電影的時代
Choplin was active in that era
Choplin就是活躍在那個時代
An era when Hollywood movies first flourished
好萊塢的電影最開始興盛的一個時代
At the same time it is Jazz Age
同時它也是Jazz Age
it's time for jazz month
是爵士月盛行的時代
jazz month useful
爵士月有用
Yes, there are five
對 也有五
Then he also includes this
那他也包括著這個
An Era of Nightclub Nightlife
Nightclub 夜生活的一個時代
then at the same time
那麼同時呢
He is also the one seen in the upper left corner
他也是向左上角看到的那種
between men and women
男女之間這個
one era
一相並的一個時代
Let's take a look at some sounds
我們不妨來看一下一些音音
I can feel the feeling of that era
可以感受到那個時代的感覺
Please bear with me
請各位忍受一下裡面的
advertise
廣告
four seconds will continue at last
四秒最後會繼續
this is
這個是
Some Foreshadowings of Paris in the 1920s
二○年代的巴黎的一些前影
OK, let's see this
好我们这个就看到这里
Okay, what about the nightlife we ​​just mentioned, let's take a look
好那么我们刚才提到的夜生活呢我们不妨来看看
How does Jazz Age behave in this NightCog?
Jazz Age在这个NightCog里面是怎么表现的这个呢是轮奔
This is the sound of the 20th-century Jazz Age.
This is the sound of the 20th-century Jazz Age.
If you want to see more colourful images of the 20th-century,
If you want to see more colourful images of the 20th-century,
I suggest you to go back to the movies you've watched recently.
I suggest you to go back to the movies you've watched recently.
The new film, The Big Red Cross, was released in 2020.
The new film, The Big Red Cross, was released in 2020.
Of course, this is basically the poster of the movie.
Of course, this is basically the poster of the movie.
You can see the background of it.
You can see the background of it.
It is a design of Art Deco
就是Art Deco的一個設計
The entire font is characteristic of that era
整個的字體都是那個時代的特色
The one below is actually his still photo I posted.
下面那一張其實是他的劇照我貼上去的
We can also be very clear in the stills
我們也可以非常清楚的在劇照裡面
Just see his whole color woman image
就看到他整個的顏色女人的形象
life inside the picture inside
生活裡面所畫面裡面
The kind that can be conveyed in this picture
這一張畫面裡面就能夠傳達出來的那種
decadent indulgence very sensual
頹廢的放縱的非常感官的
Then it is actually a world with a very dead, floating atmosphere.
然後其實是帶有非常死的 浮朽的氣息的那種世界
And behind him, there is actually an absurd person in the heart.
還有他背後其實存在那裡的一個心靈上面的荒謹的
self-imposed exile
紙最精彌的自我放逐的
There is also a mental state that breaks with tradition
還有跟傳統發生了斷裂的那樣的一個精神狀態
This is the background of the 1920s when Lu Bicheng traveled to Europe and America
這個就是呂碧城遊歷歐美的時候的1920年代的背景
Such a prosperous and smooth scene is not the same as that of modern people.
這樣一個繁華一順的容景跟現代人的那種
Xinning's barren thorns jointly built the Western European and American world in the 1920s
新寧的荒棘是共同構築了西方歐美世界的這個20年代
Well, at least in the United States until this and that Wall Street Crash in 1929
那麼至少在美國一直要到1929年的這個那個Wall Street Crash
That's why such a world collapsed
才讓這樣的一個世界崩毀了
Then after that, it will be the long-term Great Depression era of the American economy.
那麼之後呢接下來就是長期的這個美國的經濟的大蕭條時代
So, when Lu Micheng went to Europe and America to roam
那麼所以呢當呂秘成到歐美去漫遊的時候呢
Most of the time he is in such a situation
多半的時間他都是處在這樣的一個情況之下
This is a case of his destination
這個就是他的目的地的一個情況
Then I think the reason why Lu Bicheng is in his travel notes
那麼我認為呂秘成之所以在他的遊記裡面呢
Often expresses a very melancholy mood
常常會流露出一種非常憂鬱的情緒
There is also a feeling of boredom and vulgarity.
還有一種厭氣繁俗的一個感覺呢
On the other hand, he has a kind of sincerity for luxury, beauty, luxury, splendor, etc.
還有另外一方面他對於奢華美麗豪奢燦爛等等的一種誠意
These two emotions exist at the same time
這兩種情緒是同時存在的
Well, I think it's not just about his own personal
那麼我覺得呢這除了跟他自己個人的
For example, his family is considered unfortunate.
比如說他其實家庭算是不幸
For example, his health is obviously not good.
比如說他這個身體顯然不好
He always thinks he's dying
他總是認為自己好像快要死了
wait for such factors
等等這樣的因素
In fact, it also has something to do with the general environment of the place he visited.
其實也跟他所旅遊的這個地方的大環境
are closely related
是息息相關的
The overall atmosphere is just like his soul
整體的氣氛就跟他心靈上面
What about the feeling?
所產生出來的那個感覺呢
I feel empathy
我覺得是共感的
are echoes of each other
是彼此是有所呼應的
So let's read this now
那麼我們現在來讀這個
What about Lu Bicheng's European and American Man You Road?
呂碧城的歐美曼遊路呢
I think our readers at the same time as him
我覺得我們跟他同時的讀者
It's like getting a little bit of a bargain
就好像佔到了一點便宜
Because we are looking at that time from modern times
因為我們是這個從現代去看那個時候
we can see
我們就可以看到
We can see the feeling of that whole era from behind
我們從後面可以看到那整個時代的感覺
And what about Lu Bicheng and his contemporary readers?
而呂碧城跟他同時代的讀者呢
It may not feel like this
可能不見得會有這樣的感覺
to feel his emotions
去可以體會他的那個情緒
This relationship with his environment
跟他的環境之間的這個關係
So this post-construction name is still better.
所以這個後建之名還是比較好的
well then
好那麼
Because Chinese women sold oil alone in Europe and America in the 1920s
因為中國女性她在1920年代去獨自賣油歐美
except of her own will
除了她自己的意志之外
What other factors can support her?
還有什麼因素可以支撐她呢
Then I have to pull Lu Bicheng back to
那我就必須要再重新把呂碧成拉回到
Consider it within the context of her own era
她自己的這個時代的脈絡裡面來考慮
Then in this China
那麼在這個中國
In fact, as early as the 1910s in magazines
其實早在1910年代的雜誌裡面
Mailing is a very important column
郵寄就是一個非常重要的一個欄目
Many magazines will have a mailing column
很多的雜誌裡面都會有郵寄的這一欄
Everyone likes to watch other people travel and you know why
大家都喜歡看別人去旅遊 知道為什麼
What about magazines, in fact, they are often read in women's mail
那麼雜誌呢 其實也常常看在女性的郵寄
in particular
特別是
I like looking at the lights
很喜歡看燈
schoolgirl mail
女學生的郵寄
schoolgirl's work
女學生的習作
Then of course the female student won't go anywhere far with his post
那當然女學生他的郵寄不會去什麼遠的地方
For example, when we were young, we all wrote Yangmingshan mail, right?
比方說我們小時候都寫陽明山郵寄是不是
almost like that
差不多就那樣的意思
But others are a postal
但是他人就是一個郵寄
He will become a school for girls
他就會變成女學生的這個學校
Composition education is an important part of his education.
他的教育裡面 作文教育裡面重要的一環了
This fact itself represents
這件事情本身其實就代表
From the relationship with women to the previous generation
由跟女人之間的關係跟前代
is completely different
是完全不一樣的
We'll see all kinds of women's mailings in magazines
我們在雜誌裡面會看到各式各樣女性的郵寄
Or it includes women's feelings after going out for a swim
或者是包括女性出去遊了一趟回來以後的感覺
Let's say I see a record that is
比方說我看到一個記錄就是
A first generation Liu Mei's schoolgirl
一個第一代的劉美的女學生
He wrote that when he returned to China and disembarked
他就寫到說當他回到國內下了船
Set foot on the land of Shanghai, that mess
踏上了上海的土地 那個髒亂
put him down
把他給下的
This in turn is a cultural fine-fork sense
這種反過來的一種文化的精叉感
will happen
會發生
Women's Mail of the 1910s in This Era
這個時代的1910年代的女性的郵寄
In fact, some of them are very good and quite unique.
其實有一些是很不錯的 是相當有特色的
For example, the author of this article is called Ji Zonglan
比方說這一篇 這個作者叫做紀宗蘭
What you guys see here is him on
各位在這裡看到的是他登在
Volume 11 of the Women's Magazine
婦女雜誌的一卷11號
That is, December 1915
也就是1915年的12月
December
12月
A mailing by me is called "Yue Shan Ji"
的一篇郵寄叫做《由於山寄》
what about this article
那這篇文章呢
In fact, the structure is very complete
其實結構非常的完整
He talked about this natural landscape
他講到了這個天然的風景
He spoke of what he observed as a problem with social prestige
他講到了他所觀察到的社會名聲的問題
Then he also mentioned some of his historical feelings in Guanlaoyu
那麼他也提到了自己在關懶之魚的一些歷史的感懷
So what can we say about this woman's insight?
那麼我們可以說這位女性的見識呢
actually quite remarkable
其實是相當卓越的
So at the end of this article
那麼在這個文章的結尾啊
what about the author
這個作者呢
Ji Zonglan said very confidently
紀宗蘭他非常有自信的說
what about my trip
我這一趟旅行呢
Learn from it
是由而學
learn while traveling
學而遊
this is a purposeful trip
這個是一個有目的的旅行
I'm not like those boring people in Shanghai, am I?
我可不像上海那些無聊份子對不對
I only run horses every day.
每天只會跑馬啊
watch a play what?
看戲啊什麼
steamed and sea
蒸煮與海上啊
those who are useless
那些這個沒有用的人
i am useful
我是有用的人
My study and travel are combined
我的學跟遊是結合在一起的
This is Ji Zonglan
這個是紀宗蘭呢
he is very firm
他非常堅定的呢
learn from travel
把旅行跟學
Inquiry equates travel with knowledge
詢問把旅行跟知識畫上了一個等號
So who is Ji Zonglan?
那麼季宗蘭是誰呢
Ji Zonglan was a female educator in the early Ming Dynasty
季宗蘭是明初的一位女教育家
This is the same as Lu Bicheng's early identification
這個跟呂碧成早年的認同是一樣的
So special is Ji Zonglan
那麼特別的是季宗蘭
He actually has another post
他其實還有另外一篇郵寄
It's called Guilin Travel Notes
叫做桂林旅行筆記
It was also published in the same magazine
原來也是登在同一份雜誌
It's volume four, number six, of women's magazines.
就是婦女雜誌的四卷六號
That is, in June 1918
也就是1918年的6月上面
Then this post
那麼這一篇郵寄
later renamed
後來就改名為
Renamed as Guilin Post
被更名為桂林郵寄
Is received ancient and modern mail from the inside
被收入了古今郵寄從朝裡面
His writing is the same as the past and present
他的這篇文字就跟古往今來
Mailing with the Eight Great Masters of the Tang and Song Dynasties
跟唐宋八大家的郵寄
Put it together, rise up, sit up
放在一起 平起 平坐了
good
好
then we can see something like this
那麼我們可以看到像這樣
We take this post by Ji Zonglan as a representative
我們以季宗蘭的這篇郵寄作為代表
This category of this early twentieth century woman's mailing
這一類的這個二十世紀初的女性的郵寄
they did it on purpose
他們是去刻意的
Demonstrate knowledge, study, enlightenment, view of current affairs, view of history, etc.
展現知識 學習 啟蒙 時事觀 歷史觀等等
Positive going with this big one
積極的要與這個大的這個
Some viewpoints corresponding to the trend
潮流來對應的一些觀點
a positive spirit
積極進取的一種精神
We just talked about the characteristics of this era in the 1920s
我們剛才呢 說到1920年代的這個時代的特色
So what about events in Europe and America?
那麼其實在歐美事件呢
The 1920s happened to be the tourism industry
這個20年代呢 也剛剛好是這個旅遊業
A period of particularly developed leaps and bounds
特別發達飛躍的一個時期
In this day and age, I was supposed to travel abroad
這個時代呢 本來出國旅行呢
Not so common yet, in the 20's
還不是那麼普遍的 到了20年代呢
more and more popular
就越來越普及了
What about Lubi City's roaming?
那麼呂碧城的漫遊呢
It can also be said that it is a victory
也可以說是功諷其勝
Just came across the tourism industry
剛好碰到了旅遊業的
The booming period of international tourism
國際旅遊業的發達期
we can see
我們可以看看
What about Lu Bicheng after he arrived in Europe and America?
這個呂碧城他到了歐美之後呢
Along the way, I took, for example, this transoceanic ship.
一路上搭乘了比方說跨洋的這個輪船啦
He's even been on a plane
甚至他還搭過飛機啦
Then every time he arrives
那麼他每一次到
Where did the travel agency go to book tickets?
旅行社去什么订票啦
to send luggage
要送行李啦
accept luggage
接收行李啦等等
or exchange money
或者是换钱啦
he will use
他都会使用
modern tourism services
现代的旅游业的服务
for example
比方说
For example, what is this Kirk?
比方说这个什么柯克
This Thomas Cook
这个Thomas Cook
or American Express
或者是American Express
We still use this travel service
我们现在都还用的这个旅游的服务
At that time, Lu Bi's achievements were already in use
当时的吕碧成就已经在用了
And he highly recommends
而且他非常的推荐说
If you want to travel
各位如果要去旅游的话
Be sure to use these travel industry services
一定要使用这些旅游业的服务
These make his journey
这些都让他的旅程
even traveling alone
即使是孤身独游
Traveling alone is also convenient
一个人的旅行也便利了起来
Then the same period
那么同样这个时期
how is the situation in china
中国的情况如何呢
For the first time in Lu Bicheng
在吕碧成第一次
Announced in the newspaper that he was going to start
在报纸上面宣布自己要开始进行
When traveling in Europe and America
欧美的旅行的时候
he mentioned
他就提到说
My post
我的这一篇邮寄
after writing it out
写出来以后
can be the guide of the people
可以为国人之向导
It can be used as a reference for Chinese people to go abroad
可以给中国人作为出国的参考
Since he said so
那他既然这么说
Of course, it was expected that Chinese people at that time would also have the opportunity to travel abroad like him.
當然也就是預期到當時的中國人也有機會跟他一樣出國旅遊了
Well in fact it is
那麼事實上也是如此
since 1927
從1927年開始呢
Shanghai Commercial Savings Bank they set up a travel department
上海商業儲蓄銀行他們所設了一個旅行部
started publishing a magazine called a travel magazine
就開始出版了一份雜誌叫做旅行雜誌
This is his release
這個是他的發刊詞
This travel magazine is actually published by him
這個旅行雜誌事實上他出刊的
very long release period
發行期間非常久
Published from 1927 until 1954
從1927年一直到1954年才停刊
This travel magazine is mainly for Chinese readers
這個旅行雜誌主要就是要為中國的讀者
Provide various domestic and foreign travel information
提供各種國內外的旅行的資訊
first magazine
第一份雜誌
Of course, it is a product of the consumer culture in Shanghai in the 1920s
當然就是20年代的上海的消費文化的一個產物了
His founder, Chen Guangfu, must be very sharp
他的創辦人陳光福他一定是非常敏銳的
discover to travel
發現到旅遊
will be
會是
It will be a promising industry in the future
在未來會是一個前景看好的行業
so he
所以他
not only
不但
Founded a travel magazine
創辦了旅行雜誌
And also formally applied for the establishment of China Travel Agency
而且還正式的去申請成立了中國旅行社
that is Chinese
也就是中國的
Really the first travel agency in China
真的是中國的第一家旅行社
It can be seen that in modern China
由此可見在現代中國
The development of tourism in the 1920s
在20年代旅遊業上面的發展
In fact, it did not fall behind the West
其實也並沒有落於西方之後
We can take a look at this is a travel advertisement in a travel magazine
我們可以看看這個是旅行雜誌上面所刊登的旅遊的廣告
they have routes to europe
他們有到歐洲的航線
There are airlines to the United States, and all countries in the world fly
有到美國的航線世界各國都跑
He can help you arrange luxury trains, tours, etc.
他可以幫你安排做Luxury Train去遊覽等等
So I believe that it is a good idea for readers
所以我相信對讀者就算是握油
Just sit at home and watch
也就是坐在家裡面看看就好
is also very attractive
也是很有吸引力的
I think the look of the travel magazine has witnessed
我想旅行雜誌的看型就見證了
A development of Chinese tourism
中國旅遊業的一個發展
In the 18th year of the Republic of China, that is, in 1929
民國18年也就是1929年的時候
When Bicheng was still roaming
必成仍然在漫遊的時候呢
What about this travel magazine in three volumes and six issues?
這個三卷六號的旅行雜誌呢
i found one
我發現了一個
very interesting material
挺有趣的材料
then it is
那麼就是
travel magazine announced
旅行雜誌宣布
they sponsor a
他們贊助一位
young female
年輕的女性
do it once
進行一次
long trip
長途旅行
So this is what the editor of this magazine said
那麼這個雜誌的編者是這麼說的
Please look at the framed part in the lower left corner
請各位看左下角框起來的部分
He said that our local article in this issue is called
他說我們本期呢當地篇文章叫做
Nishigata Diary Middle Small Frame Nishigata Diary
西形日記中間小框西形日記
The author is Chen Fangcheng
作者呢叫做陳方成
This lady is entertained by our company
這位女士呢是由本社招待
as a lonely woman
以一孤身女子
Crossing the East Yellow Sea from the north of Shanghai
由上海北渡東黃二海
To the three eastern provinces
往東三省
It's so far from the Trans-Siberian Railway
取到西伯利亞鐵路好遠啊
And drive
而驅
of France
法國之
Paris
巴黎
Long March tens of thousands of miles
長征數萬里
Dozens of days
廢時數十日
Why is his brave and adventurous spirit so vivid?
其勇敢冒險之精神為何如言
middle school grievances
國中熟怨
those who have heard the news
其有聞風心齊者
Cry, Chinese women, come, come together
哭 中國的女性來吧 一起來吧
join this tour
都加入這樣的旅遊
Okay, so who is Chen Fangchen?
好 那麼 陳芳辰是誰呢
Chen Fangchen is the one in the photo
陳芳辰就是照片中的這位
He is Chen Xuezhao
他是這個陳學昭
Chen Xuezhao was a quite famous female writer during the May 4th period
陳學昭是五四時期一個相當著名的女作家
Of course she is much younger than this Lu Bicheng
她當然比這個呂碧城要年輕很多
I must also say that no matter in terms of cultural identity
我也必須說不管是在文化的認同上面也好
Or political identity
或者是政治的認同上面也好
She also took a completely different path from Lu Bicheng.
她也都跟呂碧城是完全走的是不一樣的路
she is a journalism writer
她是一個新聞學的作家
also a communist
也是一個共產黨員
In the end, she should have become a CPPCC member or something.
她最後應該是有當到什麼政協之類的吧
So her life is very different from that of Lu Bicheng.
所以她跟呂碧城的人生的走向是非常不一樣的
Anyway, this travel magazine at the time
不管如何 當時的這個旅行雜誌
would think of sponsoring a woman
會想到要去贊助一個女性
He knew it was a schoolgirl with curly hair
他知道是一個流髮的女學生
He's apparently in France
他顯然是到了法國
Then after returning to China
然後回到中國之後
Accepted the sponsorship of this trip again
又接受了這個旅行的贊助
took a rather roundabout one
採取了一個相當迂迴的一個
a road
一個路
In fact, he could just go straight to
他其實很可以就直接就去
Just like Lu Bicheng
就跟呂碧成一樣
Can you just go to France?
就直接可以去法國嗎
But he has to walk
但是他卻要走路路
run to siberia
跑到西伯利亞再走
This is definitely a travel agency
這個絕對是旅行社
A set itinerary for him
幫他做的一個套裝行程
It is a specially designed itinerary
是一個特別設計過的行程
In order to highlight this journey
為的就是要凸顯這一趟旅途
is a feat
是一個壯舉
is a long march
是一個長征
So it's about this woman
那麼要講的就是這個女性
alone
孤身一人
Being able to take risks like pan male spirit
能夠冒險泛男這樣的精神
Then of course his request
那麼當然他的訴求
is a progressive
就是一個進步的
independent brave revolutionary women
獨立的 勇敢的 革命的女性
then obviously this
那麼很明顯的這個
Chen Xuezhao represents the brave
陳學昭他所代表的這個勇敢的
What about the image of a woman?
女性的 女人的形象呢
Mixiang Yuyi
跟那個迷祥羽衣
with a feather on the head
頭上帶著一隻羽毛
wearing tightly embroidered clothes
穿著緊繡的衣服的
Lu Bicheng's
呂碧成的那個
The image of an oil seller is completely different
賣油家的形象是完全不可同日而語的
But we can know from this example
不過我們由這樣的例子就可以知道
also as a lonely
同樣作為一個孤身獨有
woman traveling alone
一個人旅行的女性
In fact, Lu Bicheng didn't punish his companions either.
其實呂碧成他也不罰他的同伴
Chen Xuezhao is a living example
像陳學昭就是一個活生生的例子
then indeed like this
那麼確實像這樣
A person is able to board the journey by himself
一個人能夠自己登上旅程
Maybe it really is a woman of the twentieth century
或許真的就是二十世紀的女性
twentieth century women
二十世紀的女性
A new option when traveling
去旅行的時候一個新的選擇
This is really a woman from the previous generation
這個是前代的女性真的
no way to enjoy
沒有辦法享受到的
Women's Lives in the Late Qing and Early Ming Dynasties
清末明初的女性的生命
It actually happened
其實是真的出現了
many, many new possibilities
很多很多新的可能性
There are so many excellent women
那麼優秀的女性實在是太多了
Lu Bicheng can be said to belong to this generation
呂碧成他可以說是這一輩
Just one of the great women
傑出女性當中的一員而已
But if we talk about travel
不過如果我們由旅行來說的話
Then their trip to Europe and America
那麼他們的歐美之遊
In fact, his characteristics
其實他的特點
It's not that he's traveled more than others
並不是說他走的路比別人多
go farther than others
去的地方比別人遠
Or his Jianwen is more broadcast than others
或者是他的建文比別人廣播
But I think he especially emphasized
而是我覺得他特別的去強調了
Neither learning nor adventure
不是學問也不是冒險
It's the level of roaming
而是漫遊的那個層面
His travel notes are called European and American Wandering Road
他的遊記就叫做歐美漫遊路
This trip from 1926
從1926年開始的這趟旅行
He doesn't want to be a citizen
他也不想求去公民
do not want to study
也不想求學
I don't want to think about saving the country every year
也不想隔年年從來沒想過要救國
The few examples we gave earlier
在我們前面舉的那幾個例子
have a purpose
都有目的性
But Lu Bicheng's roaming
但是呂畢成的這一趟漫遊
roaming
卻就是漫遊
no purpose
沒有目的的
I think at this level
我覺得在這個層面上面
he really read a bar
他真的讀數一格
that belonged outside the entire tourism discourse of the time
是其屬於當時的整個的旅遊論述之外的
But maybe that's why
但是也或許正因如此
When we read Lu Bicheng's travel notes today
到今天我們來讀呂畢成的遊記的時候
We also often feel his intention to read Chuang
我們還往往感受到他讀創的心意
deodorize
去味
Then the last period of time, I want to come
那么最后的一段时间呢我就想要来
Let me share with you where Lu Bichen is
跟各位分享一下吕碧晨到底在
what is written in the mail
邮寄里面写了什么呢
So
那么
Traveling in Europe and America is basically written following his travel footprints
欧美漫游录基本上就是跟着他的这个旅行的足迹而写的
It started from San Francisco in the west of the United States
是从美国的这个西部的旧金山开始
then to chicago
然后呢到芝加哥
then to new york
然后到纽约
took a boat across the Atlantic
坐了船 渡过大西洋
to Paris, France
到了法国的巴黎
Then take the train
然后呢搭上火车
go to switzerland
去瑞士
Arrived in Geneva to take over
到了这个日内瓦保揽
Huguangshan Temple
这个湖光山寺
And then to Milan, Italy
然后呢到意大利的米兰
Ancient Lawrence
古罗伦斯
Rome
罗马
then back to paris
然后再回到巴黎
Then from Paris through Switzerland and Italy
然后呢又从巴黎经过瑞士意大利
What is this Napoleon?
这个什么拿破里啊
Pompeii, Venice
庞贝啊威尼斯啊
In the end it was there
最后呢还到过
he took the plane
他搭了飞机
For the first time in his life, he took a plane
他人生的第一次搭了飞机
Arrived in Australia
到了澳国的
vienna
维也纳
Then take the train
然后呢再搭火车
to berlin
到柏林
After returning to Paris?
再从回到巴黎之后呢
exist
在
this
这个
cross the sea
渡海
arrive
到
go to london
伦敦去
Then to Paris, then to Switzerland
再跑到巴黎 再跑到瑞士
Finally settled down in Switzerland
最後就是在瑞士定居下來
So in the beginning he made Paris his center
所以一開始他是以巴黎作為他的中心
But in the end he chose to settle in Switzerland
但是最後他是選擇在瑞士定居
Of course this journey is very complicated
當然這個旅程非常的複雜
But even from our perspective today,
不過就算是以我們今天的角度來看
We also have to say it's a luxury trip
我們也不得不說 這真是奢侈的旅行
is a dream trip
是一個夢幻旅程
at the beginning of the journey
在旅程的一開始
We just said he started in San Francisco
我們剛剛說他是從舊金山開始的
Well, Journey Bicheng actually described it at the very beginning
那麼 旅畢程其實一開始就描述了
Before he left for Europe from San Francisco
他從舊金山準備要出發去歐洲之前
he used to visit hollywood
他曾經去游覽好萊塢
Whether he writes about Hollywood
不管是他寫好萊塢也好
Or he can write about Paris or London later.
或者他之後寫巴黎 寫倫敦也好
All revealed his love for the city's prosperity
都透露出他對於這個城市的繁華的
a yearning and nature
一種嚮往跟性質
Well, we just mentioned
那麼我們剛才已經提過
What about America in the 1920s?
1920年代的這個美國呢
Is the most developed era of the film industry
是電影工業最發達的一個時代
Then the halo of the star is of course the moment of this holy collection
那麼明星的光環當然是這個聖集一時了
So, Lu Bicheng wants to go to Hollywood for a tour?
所以呢 呂碧成會想要去好萊塢游覽呢
In fact, it is also a matter of course
其實也是理所當然
So what happens when he gets to Hollywood?
那麼他到了好萊塢之後呢
In particular, he wrote that he went to visit the star's residence
就特別寫到他去參觀明星的住宅
He used very, very wonderful early words
他用了非常非常漫妙的早立的文字呢
To describe what he sees is not a star
去描述他所看到的不是明星
but where the stars live
而是明星所住的地方
But the interesting thing is
不過有趣的是
Just like when we read "A Dream of Red Mansions"
就像是我們讀《紅樓夢》的時候
we would say that one has one's residence
我們會說一個人有一個人的住所
Where does Lin Daiyu live?
這個林黛玉住的地方呢
It must be regarded as the movie of Sensenlong
就一定要奉為森森龍影戲戲
have pigs
要有豬子
So what about the place where Xiubao lives?
那麼這個修寶差住的地方呢
Bili Teng Luo
一定就是要必立藤羅
There is a cold feeling
有一種冷森森的感覺
So where does Jia Baoyu live?
那麼甲寶玉住的地方呢
it has to be this
就一定要是這個
There is a daughter's smell, a powdery smell
有女兒氣 有脂粉氣
Then take Lin Long Baoge and so on
那麼以林龍寶格等等
Where do you live?
住的地方呢
Just like this person's temperament, temperament
就跟這個人的氣質 性情
Even fate is linked together
甚至命運是連在一起的
When visiting the homes of Hollywood superstars
在參觀好萊塢巨星的宅底的時候
He played the reading method of Dream of Red Mansions
他就發揮了這個紅樓夢讀法
Compare the atmosphere of this superstar's house with the image of this star
把這個巨星的宅底的氣氛跟這個明星的形象
His status in Hollywood and so on made a link
他在好萊塢的地位等等都做了一個連結
So let's take an example
那麼不妨舉一個例子
He seemed to be interested in this at the time
他好像對這個當時
In fact, the Hollywood star who died not long ago
其實剛剛才死去不久的好萊塢的大明星
It is a special favorite of Panentino's relatives and friends
是泛倫鐵諾特別的親友獨鍾
Although I think he said with a little false confidence
雖然我覺得他有一點假信心的說
Oops, Panentino isn't very good looking.
哎呀其實泛倫鐵諾長得不怎麼樣
Italian men are much prettier than him
利大利的男人比他漂亮的可多了去了
But in fact he is very interested in Panentino
但是事實上他對泛倫鐵諾是很有興趣的
Then he specifically mentions
那麼他特別提到
When he visited the former residence of Panentino
他參觀泛倫鐵諾的故居的時候
found the atmosphere of this place very heavy
發現這個地方的氣氛非常的沉重
vocal range sound forest
音域音森
No wonder the owner of this house can't live long
怪不得這個房子的主人不能夠長壽
but he
但是呢他
He also paid special attention to the original center of the house
他還特別的注意到房子的原中
There are all kinds of exotic flowers and plants
有各式各樣的奇異的花草
There is a special flower
其中有一株特別的花
He said there was an unknown
他說有不知名之一本
a strange plant
一個奇異的植物
just be a flower
翹然只做一朵花
Then the color is very, very gorgeous
那麼色澤非常非常的艷麗交焰
And this flower is very big
而且這個花非常大朵
But because it's too big
但是因為它太大了
this gold can't hold it
這個金撐不住它
so it hangs down
所以它是垂下來的
relying on the sidelines
依測於一旁
Then he used a very interesting description to say
那麼他用了一個非常有趣的形容說
The bully of endless flowers
這個花若蘊無窮之欺怨者
i think i don't need to say more
我想我不用多說
Then what he describes is, on the surface, a strange flower
那麼他所描寫的表面上是一朵奇花異彙
In fact, it is equivalent to
其實就等於是
Handsome, elegant, a symbiosis of Panentino's idol
俊美的 秀逸的 泛伦铁诺的偶像的一个协真
or a photo
或者是小照吧
A little photo of the heart, a reflection of the heart
内心的小照吧 内心的反射吧
Then, Lu Bichen said
那么 吕碧晨说
Then when he sailed across the Atlantic
之后 当他横度大西洋的时候
On the ship, I also dreamed that Panentino came to give him the name of the place.
在轮船上面 还梦见了泛伦铁诺来给他地名骗呢
I think this can really be used as a case for psychoanalysis
这个 我想真的是可以作为心理分析的一个case
Then we might as well take a look with you
那么我们也不妨跟大家一起来看看
Mulan Ruji in Paris mentioned in the travel notes
游记里面写到的巴黎的 木兰如吉
What is this place called Mulan Ruji?
这个地方 什么叫做木兰如吉呢
can you guess
可以猜到吗
Mulan Ruji
木兰如吉
Mulan Ruji, Mulan's Nurse
木兰如吉 木兰的护士
It is the Hongmofang as we know it today.
就是我们今天所熟知的红墨坊
Well, Lu Bichen described in great detail
那么 吕碧晨非常详细地描述了
The performance he saw in this Red Ink Workshop
他在这个红墨坊所看到的演出
may wish to read his text
不妨讀一下他的文字
Well, this is the very early text of the day
那麼這個是當日是很早一的文字
He said that I will not read this long-term relationship
他說這個長鐘時間的關係我就不念了
Basically, feel it
基本上各位感覺一下
Just look at the words and condemnation here.
光是看一下這裡面的用字譴詞就可以了
He's saying the show is the actors on stage
他是說這場表演是台上的演員
All stars performing
都是表演的各式各樣的星星
There's Mars, there's Venus, there's the moon, whatever.
有火星 有金星 有月亮什麼的
Everyone is dressed like a star in the sky
每一個人就打扮得像是天上的星星一樣
very beautiful
非常的美麗
His description is of course a kind of shaping is a very strong and disgusting feeling
他的描寫當然是一種塑造的是一個非常濃厭的感覺
His writing is a performance in itself
他的文字本身就是一個演出了
Just like Mulan Ruji's performance on the stage is as exquisite
就跟台上的木蘭如極的演出是一樣的精美的
But I think we can also feel
不過我覺得我們也可以感受到
When he wrote in such an early-established classical Chinese
當他使用這麼早立的文言來寫作的時候
very interesting
很有趣的
It’s obviously a western scene, it’s a modern scene
明明是西方的 明明是現代的一個場景
Written by him in such classical Chinese
被他用這樣的文言一寫
Why do you seem to be eavesdropping
怎麼好像就偷聽
Has it become the advanced of Chinese classical imagination?
變成了中國古典想像的先進了呢
Do you feel that way?
有這樣的感覺嗎
Then, Lu Bicheng's writing in classical Chinese
那麼 呂碧成的文言文的書寫
An example of transforming Western modernity into Chinese tradition
把西方的現代轉換成中國傳統的例子
In fact, there are many
其實還有很多
Let's say he writes about what the symbols of Hollywood are
比方說他寫好萊塢的象徵是什麼
Is it just the words on the mountain?
是不是就山上那幾個字
That word Hollywood
那一個字 Hollywood
But it was like this
不過當時是這樣的
he described what he saw
他形容 他所看到的
He said
他說
On the one hand, I saw this Cuifeng promoted
一面就看到這個翠峰促起
After solar reflection?
日輝反射以後呢
Yan dwarf overflows like a queen of heaven
燕矮四溢如天后靈虛
The fairy came out again
又是仙女又跑出來了
Then Yu Hui's kindness is a treasure
那麼 餘輝善為寶寄
Flickering among the clouds and Weng Yi
閃爍於雲霞翁溢間
What list?
榜 什麼榜啊
We only know the piano list
我們只知道琴榜
There is also a list here
這邊也有榜
Bangda from the mountainside approx.
榜大自於山腰約
hollywood
好萊塢盡
He used static
他用 靜
To translate the Land of Hollywood Land
來翻譯 Hollywood Land的那個 Land
just use this word
就用這一個字
Let's take this from a modern movie
就讓我們現代電影裡面的這個
this sensuality
這個聲色
Naturally, it is the same as the fairy needle sword in our traditional imagination
自然就跟我們傳統想像裡面的這個仙針寶劍
A wonderful association arose
產生了一個奇妙的聯想
Like this kind of tension between the text and the object of description
像這種文字跟描寫對象中間的一個緊張的
a relationship that must be worked out
一個必須要磨合的一個關係
In Lu Bicheng's this
在呂碧成的這個
It can also be seen in the word
這個詞裡面也可以看到
This Lu Bicheng wrote a lot of words in his overseas Jianwen
這個呂碧成用這個他在海外的建文寫了很多的詞
This is also one of the reasons why later people have a high evaluation of his words.
這個也是後來的人對他的詞作有很高的評價的原因之一
Because it was impossible for other writers at that time
因為當時其他寫詞的人是不可能
like he used such subjects
像他用這樣的題材的
Let's look at an example
我們看一個例子就好
This is what he wrote about the Eiffel Tower
這個是他寫巴黎鐵塔
Then I won't read it either
那我同樣也就不念了
but look at
但是各位看看
It's really old and new
真的是新舊東西病成
Thousands of reds give birth to crows, afraid that the soul of spring will escape
萬紅生烏 怕春魂逸散
But what about Kyushu first stationed in the sky to inspect
可是呢 九州先駐 駐天巡視
Iron to Ling Kong
鐵往靈空
He was talking about the buildings of the station at that time
他講的是當時的駐鐵的建築
This is the benchmark of modern architecture
這是現代建築的標桿
So he is very clever
所以他非常巧妙的
The kind that combines modern architecture with classical nephrite thermostats
把現代的建築跟古典的軟玉溫箱的那種
imaginatively combined
想像的結合在一起
Or look at the second
又或者是看第二缺
Do not turn over the old score
通標別翻舊譜
He took the Eiffel Tower
他把這個巴黎鐵塔
It is likened to this standard iron pillar
比喻成這個通標鐵柱
This is the Age of Empires
也就是這個帝國時代
The pillar of the national border erected by the Eastern Han Dynasty
東漢所立下的這個國界的那根柱子
Is a symbol of the empire's industry
是帝國的工業的象徵
Eiffel Tower
他把巴黎鐵塔
A symbol of industry compared to the traditional Chinese empire
比做中國傳統帝國的工業的象徵
Stay in Sunny Days with Jin Xian in the Western Regions
一駐晴天跟晉賢西域
almost as high as the sun
差不多要跟太陽一樣高
then look down
那麼往下看去
This car is as small as an ant
這個車子就像是螞蟻一樣的小
back around
回到在四周
So this lack of words for this blood tyrant from the iron tower
所以這個血霸離鐵塔的這一缺詞
very cleverly put this
就非常巧妙地把這個
In his heart he can never let go
他心目中永遠不能夠放開的
Chinese classical tradition
中國的古典的傳統
with what he has seen and heard in the West
跟他所見聞的西方的景物
make a bond
做一個結合
But always this combination
但是始終這個結合
It seems to me that there is always friction
在我看來是一直有著摩擦
But this friction also creates some fun
但是這個摩擦也創造了一些趣味
Then Yubicheng wrote a lot of
那麼宇碧城寫了非常非常多的
words from overseas
海外見聞的詞
For example, he wrote about the lake in Geneva
比方說他寫日內瓦的湖
Bingshan writes about the palace and so on.
冰山 寫皇宮等等非常多
So lest it often presents such a similar fun
那麼以免往往都會呈現這樣類似的趣味
When we were reading Lu Bicheng's post
我們在讀呂畢成的郵寄的時候
You will find that as his Lu Cheng advances
會發現隨著他的呂成的推進
He seems to be getting more and more tired of people
他似乎對於人士越來越厭煩
Become more and more alienated from human relationships
對於人際關係也越來越疏離
Of course, this may be related to his growing religious feelings.
這當然可能跟他的宗教情懷也越來越強烈有關
In the end he chose to live by Lake Geneva in Switzerland
最後他是選擇居住在瑞士的日內華湖邊
Instead of returning to his original Lu-shaped center
而不是返回他原來的呂形中心
Paris metropolitan to permanent residency
巴黎大城市去長駐
I think this residency choice actually reflects
我想這個駐居的選擇其實就反映了
Some changes in his own mood
他自己心境上的一些轉變
But we have to get back to reality
不過我們必須回到現實
Regardless of whether Lu Bicheng is so rich
不管呂畢成是不是這麼有錢
Of course he is very rich to be able to do such a trip
他當然是很有錢才能夠做這樣的旅行
but whether you have money or not
但是不管你有沒有錢
It doesn't matter it's the 1920s
也不管那是1920年代
Or our 2010s today
或者是我們今天的2010年代
To make a person whether a man or a woman
要讓一個人不管是男人還是女人
Traveling alone in a foreign country for a long time
一個人在異國長期旅行
Actually it won't be one
其實都不會是一件
easy is
容易的是
then this difficult
那麼這種艱難
this loneliness
這種寂寞
this feeling of loneliness
這種孤獨的感覺
is a
是一種
We lobby for constant
我們說客圖求恆
Yes or no
是不是
is a time-traveling
就是一種跨越時間
Leap across
跨越跨越
across
跨越
even i want to cross race
甚至我想跨越種族
everyone on the go
每一個人在旅途當中
there will be a general feeling
都會有一種普遍的情感
I previously
我以前
i forgot what time
我忘記是什麼時候了
But I remember I read a
但我記得我讀過一篇
read a british book
讀過一本英國人寫的
book about travel
有關於旅行的書
in that book
在那本書裡面
he used several paintings
他用了幾幅畫
Well, it just so happened that the painter
那麼剛好這個畫家
Also one of my favorite painters
也是我非常喜歡的一個畫家
let me share with you
我跟大家分享一下
good
好
This is also living in the 1919th century
這個同樣也是生活在1919世紀
Late to 20th century
末期到20世紀
about age
大概有年年代吧
left and right one
左右的一個
contemporary british painters
當代的英國的畫家
sorry american painter
對不起 美國的畫家
Called Edward Hopper
叫做Edward Hopper
What about him
他呢
My favorite painting is life
最喜歡畫都是生活
maybe i believe
可能我相信
Everyone has seen his clothes painting
所有的人都看過他的衣服畫
that is
就是
On a street is a storefront
在一條街上就是一個店面
The inside of the store looks very bright
店面裡面非常光明的樣子
how many people are sitting inside
裡面坐著幾個人
But it seems bright
但好像很光明吧
but you just have a
但你就是會有一種
endless
無盡的
Empty
空虛的
Feelings of consideration
顧及的感覺
Then what he expressed
那麼他表達的這種
what about this emotion
這種情緒呢
deeply moved me
深深的讓我覺得感動
Then he often draws this kind of
那麼他常常在畫這種
The feeling of this consideration in the city
都市裡面的這個顧及的感覺
And the feeling of consideration during the trip
還有旅途裡面的顧及的感覺
Just now Wang Fu specifically mentioned
剛才王傅特別提到
travel
旅行啦
train
火車啦
hotel
旅館啦
He actually contains all these things
這些東西他其實都蘊含著
A deep association and charm
很深的一種聯想跟韻味
It can be expressed in these paintings
這些畫裡面都可以表達得出來
This is the journey he expressed
他表達的就是這種旅途
inside this
裡面的這種
lonely
寂寞
isolated from others
跟人隔絕
feeling of inaccessibility
無法接近的感覺
A sort of
一種
aphasia feeling
失語的感覺
you can't talk to people
你不能跟人交談
Or the feeling that there is no language at all
或者是語言上根本不相通的感覺
will be in these paintings
都會在這些畫作裡面呢
vaguely
隱隱約約的
express it
表達出來
What about these paintings?
這幾幅畫呢
Must be from the 1920s
應該都是1920年代的作品
we can see
我們可以看看
Some words are very clear
有一些話是很明確的表現
and it's all a woman
而且都是一個女人
It's clear she's on the road
很明確的表現她在旅途當中
For example, the upper left corner and the upper right corner follow
比方說左上角右上角跟
lower right corner
右下角
a woman on the go
一個女人在旅途當中
What about the lower left corner?
左下角呢
she didn't tell you she was traveling
她沒告訴你她在旅行
But what?
可是呢
do not know why
不知道為什麼
I just feel like she's traveling
我就是感覺她在旅行
She is at a rest stop on a trip
她在一個旅行的休息站
a resting place in the middle
中間一個休息的地方
no one to talk to
沒有人可以說話
Kuji
姑吉
cold
冷
We can see that
我們可以看到
she
她
to get a coffee cup
為了要拿咖啡杯
That's why I took off my gloves
所以才把手套拿下來
but what about the other hand
但是另外一隻手呢
Some people carry such heavy
還有人就帶著那麼厚重的
a glove
一個手套
She can't even take off her hat and clothes
她的帽子衣服都不能脫
so cold so empty
那麼冷那麼空虛
so guji
那麼姑吉的
a feeling
一個感覺
then every time you see
那麼每一次看到
this
這個
Hopperized these
Hopper化的這些
What about female tourists?
女性的旅遊者呢
Actually reminds me of 1920
其實都讓我想到1920年
Tourist City Roaming in Europe and America
在歐美漫遊的旅必城
yes
是
Li Bicheng also often wrote in his travel notes
李碧成在游记里面也常常写到
He will come into contact with different people during this trip
他在这个旅行当中会跟不一样的人接触
For example, the person who sold him the ticket
比方说卖票给他的人啦
Or a passenger in the same car
或者是同车的旅客啦
He also quarrels with passengers in the same car
他还会跟同样同车的旅客吵架
Or a strange teenager who went with him to swim Lake Geneva
或者是跟他一起去游日内瓦湖的一个陌生的少年啦
Wait, he's in contact with people
等等 他是跟人接触的
But what about that feeling of loneliness and emptiness?
但是呢 那种孤极的空虚的感觉
but never seemed to leave him
却似乎从来没有离开过他
And what's interesting
而且呢 有趣的是
What about his sense of isolation and ordering?
他的那种孤极感跟梳理感呢
He often expresses it in a negative way
他往往会用一个反面的方式来表达的
For example, he would specifically write
比方说他会特别写到
Um
嗯
When he travels, he often laughs at himself
他在旅行当中呢 常常会自己笑自己
He'll say he's always smiling
他会说他自己是笑口常开
Why because only one person doesn't smile so what
为什么 因为只有一个人不笑又能怎样呢
Well, the helplessness he showed
好 他表现出来的这种非常无奈的
ah one feels good
啊 一个感觉 好
or is it
或者是呢
He used a certain method to create a particularly deserted
他用某一种方式去营造特别冷清
or a particularly lively scene
或者是特別熱鬧的場景
But whether it's deserted or lively
但是呢 不管是冷清或者是熱鬧
Lu Bicheng's figure as a lonely woman
呂碧成作為一個孤獨的女人的身影呢
will be more prominent
就會更加的突出
Let's look at two examples
我們來看兩個例子
This is the first example
這是第一個例子
One time she was stuck in London
有一次呢 她被困在倫敦
It's been half a year
整整有半年之久
she hates london
她非常討厭倫敦
Why
為什麼
It is clear
很明顯
At that time, the air pollution in London was very serious.
那個時候倫敦的空氣無染很嚴重
Plus London is already foggy
再加上倫敦本來就多霧
When she was there, it was winter
她在那裡的時候呢 碰到的是冬天
She is not used to the food
吃的東西她都不習慣
How about going to this Japanese restaurant in the alley next door for tofu?
去隔壁巷子的這個日本餐館吃豆腐呢
counting money piece by piece
一片一片算錢
she can't stand it
她真是覺得受不了
How to do it
怎麼辦呢
she says
她說
Encounter, count the days, she knows this is
碰到 算算日子她知道這個是
Lunar cooking department
農曆的廚系了
in China
在中國
Her relatives and friends should be celebrating
她的親戚朋友們都應該在慶祝
at reunion
在團圓
She is a solo artist
她卻是孤身藝人
So what about Lu Bicheng?
那麼呂碧成怎麼辦呢
she says
她說
This is New Year's Eve
這個是農曆的除夕
So I dress myself up beautifully
所以呢 我把自己特別打扮的漂漂亮亮的
I walked alone to the hotel's special restaurant to eat
我一個人走到旅館的特別餐廳去用餐
what does he describe himself in
他形容自己穿什麼
He is wearing a black section Hiratzu Hiratzu is a method of embroidery
他穿著黑段平津 平津是一種繡花的方法
This wrist coat embroidered with He, He, what a lonely image
這個繡著赫的腕衣 赫 多麼孤高的一個形象
The black segment is embroidered with golden hex
黑段上面繡著金色的赫
in golden shoes and bead jars
踩著金色鞋子 戴著珠罐
He likes to wear pearls in a bead jar
他很喜歡用戴珍珠 珠罐
He said it is very cheap to buy pearls in China
他說在中國買珍珠特別便宜
wearing a bead jar
戴著珠罐
like a fairy like a celestial being also like this image
就像 一個仙女 像一個天上人也這樣的形象
Go to the hotel's special restaurant
走到旅館的特別餐廳去
He said I look like I'm a fool
他說 我自己看起來都覺得自己是胡天胡地
That is to say, Hu Tianhudi means to look like a man in heaven
就是說 胡天胡地的意思就是像天上人
It's not what people in the world mean
就不是世間人的意思
Consider what he has built for himself
想想看他所為自己營造的
Such a deserted and lonely image
這樣冷清而孤高的一個形象
image or vice versa at the busiest moment
形象 又或者相反的 在最熱鬧的時候
This is that he has finally arrived in Switzerland.
這個呢 是他最後已經到了瑞士了
so he's there and he's just that rich
那麼他在 而且他就 就這麼有錢
He lives by the lake in Geneva
他住在日內瓦的湖邊 打開窗子就看到日內瓦湖
But he said that because of meeting Jieqing, the rest of the night
但是呢 他說因為碰到潔慶 下面整個晚上呢
It's all from Guyue Xuantian, he can't do anything, he can't sleep at all
都是骨月宣天的 他根本沒有辦法 根本沒有辦法睡覺
So he felt that he was too lonely
於是呢 他覺得說 這個自己實在太寂寞了
Because when you're alone, you're in this busy place where you're bothered
因為 當你一個人的時候 你在熱鬧的 這個處煩惱之場呢
You will feel more sick, not to mention he is not worried about poverty
就會感覺更加的疾療 何況他擺憂貧疾呢
As for why he puts his worries on poverty, of course, that's another matter.
那至於他究竟為什麼擺憂貧疾呢 當然是另外一回事了
So it’s okay to pretend you can’t hear me, what should I do in the end?
那麼假裝聽不見也不行 最後怎麼辦呢
He just decided to say, then I'll join them.
他就決定說 那我就加入他們好了
So which issue of his costume did he pay so much attention to his image?
於是呢 他哪一期禮裝 他這麼注意形象
I still have to dress up, dress up before going out
還是要打扮了 打扮了才能出門
then just
然後呢 就
just go outside for a walk
就到外面去散步
found outside
發現外面的是
From people like branches, lanterns and bamboo sky
由人如枝 燈彩竹天
Red and green rubber halo on the lake surface, pearls of water blooming
湖面紅綠膠暈 珠水光流綻
Unique banquet
悠宴獨絕
at this time
這個時候
This is Baihuahui
這個叫做百花慧
this festival
這個節慶
All of them are holding a paper bag inside
所有的人手裡都拿著一個紙袋裡面
All tax-deductible materials
都是減稅的材質
lose when you see someone
看到人就丟
Seems like they're not splashing water
好像還好他們不是潑水
They are just splash material
他們是潑材質而已
So
那麼
Even the body of the police will be thrown away is the material
連警察的身上都會被丟的都是材質
that law does not prohibit
那個法律也不會禁止
So
那麼
what did he say
他說呢
what about this time
這個時候呢
Both father and daughter are wearing bags
父女都是穿著包包的衣服
And the collars are big
而且領子都大大的
so
所以
Once the material is thrown away?
那個材質一丟過來呢
They all ran into the clothes
都跑到那個衣服裡面去了
So
那麼
Some people will pull this collar off of others
還有人會把別人的這個領子拉開
Then what
然後呢
Pour all the materials in
把所有的材質都倒進去
So
那麼
Someone deliberately patted someone on the shoulder
也有人故意去拍一下人家的肩膀
As soon as you look back, quickly put this material
一回頭就趕快把這個材質
Throw it in someone's face, etc.
往人家臉上一扔等等
this prank goes
這個惡作去
Then he was thrown out
那麼他就被人家扔了
made him that this
弄的他那個這個
I can't keep my eyes open
眼睛就睜不開
It's like he's at war
他就好像打仗一樣
he lost
他輸了
he fled back to the hotel
他就逃回旅館
he said it doesn't matter
他說沒有關係
i'm ready tomorrow
我明天準備好了
again
再來
So the next day he took the weapon himself
於是第二天他自己也拿了武器
Just a bag of material
就是一袋材質
Then there's a towel over it
然後上面還蓋著一塊手巾
pretend you don't have a weapon
假裝自己沒有武器
wait until someone walks in
等到有人走進的時候
It was only then that I suddenly threw this material on someone else.
才突然先開把這個材質丟到人家身上
Then he is particularly visual
那麼他就特別特別的形象化的
To describe how he participated in the Hundred Flowers Festival
去描述他怎麼樣參加這個百花會
How do you hang out with everyone?
怎麼樣的跟大家悉鬧在一起
we can really imagine
我們真的可以想像
The hotel where I was alone in London
那個本來獨自一個人在倫敦的旅館
But also stubbornly wear beaded gold and aluminum
還要固執著穿戴珠觀金鋁的
This must-see city in the lake, sky and lake
這個湖天湖地的旅必城
Arrived at the Hundred Flowers Festival
到了百花會上
but he wants to let go
他卻要放下身段
chasing after the crowd like a child
就像小孩子一樣在人群裡面追趕著
Passionate about planting this material
旺情的去拋植這個材質
In fact, the loneliness of that journey
事實上那個旅途的孤寂感
It's not bothering me at all
一點都沒有因為這煩惱
Or lighten up with laughing scenes
或者是嘻笑的場面而減輕
Instead, we see more
我們反而更加的看到了
the sorrow in his heart
他內心的那種憂愧
The loneliness of the figure
身影的孤獨
Against the backdrop of this external joyful environment
在這個外在的歡樂的環境的襯托施下
In fact, it is more prominent
其實是更加的凸顯了
The interesting thing is that Lu Bicheng said
各有趣的是呂碧成說
This Hundred Flowers War is actually an elegant battle
這個百花大戰其實是一場雅戰
everyone is silent
大家都不說話的
Because all the people here are international
因為來的都是國際人士
We don't speak the same language
大家的語言是不相通的
So it's right to throw away the paper if you borrow it.
所以借了人就丟紙就對了
no need to speak
不需要講話的
so you can also say
所以你也可以說
For Lu Bicheng
對呂碧成來講
This is the most convenient way to integrate into a foreign country
這是一個最方便融入異國的一種方式
Because you just open yourself up
因為你就開放自我就好了
You don't need to be able to communicate in language
你也不需要在語言上面能夠溝通
can be integrated into the environment
就可以融入環境
At the end of the Hundred Flowers Conference
在這個百花大會的最後的結尾
Lu Bicheng also made it very clear
呂碧成他卻也說得很明白
He said that night
他說這一天的晚上
like a dream
就好像是一場夢一樣
After all, his life experience is in vain
畢竟他的身世飄零
identity of his culture
他的文化的認同
His love on this journey
他的這個旅途中的相情
His self-admiration and so on
他的孤方自賞等等
They can only temporarily participate in such a Hundred Flowers Conference
都只能夠暫時地在這樣一場百花大會上面
just be liberated
得到解放而已
What about after the big dream trip?
那麼大夢出行之後呢
He is still going back to the home of the wandering lonely traveler
他仍就要回到那個飄零的孤獨的旅人的
in this situation
這個情境裡面
Of course it's in his mail
當然在他的郵寄裡面
Also mentioned a lot of this more practical issue
還提到很多這個比較實際的問題
For example, how can I get into trouble booking a ticket?
比方說訂票怎麼樣會出麻煩
sometimes dangerous
有的時候會碰到危險
In fact, traveling alone
其實一個人的旅行
Of course it can be dangerous
當然是有可能是危險的
Then Lu Bicheng is in the post office
那麼呂碧成在郵寄裡面
Keep mentioning that he's actually in constant danger
不斷地提到他其實是常常處在危險當中
Unknowingly or luckily escaped
而不自知或者是幸運的逃過
Here's another story lurking out there
這是潛伏在那裡的另外一個故事
Of course I don't have time to share with you today
今天當然就沒有時間跟大家分享了
The highest point of Lu Bicheng's mailing
呂碧成的郵寄的最高點
It should be when he was in 1929
應該就是他在1929年的時候
Accepted the invitation of the World Animal Protection Association
接受了萬國保護動物會的邀請
to vienna for the congress
到維也納去參加大會
At this time Lu Bicheng is a very devout Buddhist
這個時候呂碧成他是非常虔誠的佛教徒
He sang that vegetarian food does not kill
他唱到素食不殺聲
But he attended the conference as a
但是他作為一個參加大會
and the public speaking guests
而且公開發表演講的來賓
We still see this image
我們還是看到的是這樣的形象
The person is the one who wears pearls, steps on golden shoes, and eyebrow pencil
人就是那個帶著珠觀 踩著金鞋 眉筆
The image of Lu Bicheng dressed like a peacock
像孔雀一般的呂碧成的盛裝的形象
So he will always insist on literary creation
所以他在文學創作上面永遠都在堅持
Writing classical Chinese and old poems
寫作文言跟舊題詩詞
seems to be i independent
似乎是一世獨立的
He will always write in an old style
他永遠都要以一個舊的文體去寫作
So it is often classified as a conservative in literature
所以常常都會被歸類為文學上面的一個保守派
or old hands
或者是手舊份子
Well, on the surface
那麼從表面上面來看的話
He is this maverick in terms of behavior
他在行為處事上面卻是這個特立獨行的
Then his behavior and his insistence on style
那麼他的行為處事跟他在文體上面的堅持
It seems that if we just said at the beginning
看起來如果我們剛才一開始所說
Looks like it's been stolen or contradicted
好像是被盜而馳或者是矛盾的
But in fact, we might as well think about it the other way around
但是其實我們不妨反過來想
When he stands in such a mighty modern
當他站在這麼強大的一個現代的
when inside the red oil of the times
時代的紅油裡面的時候
does he want it
他要嗎
just indifferent
就是明完無感
but he is not
但他不是
so what
所以呢
He is like Lu Bicheng
他就是像呂畢成這樣
there is such a non-inquiry
有這麼不詢的
a rebellious personality
叛逆的一個個性
Only in such a powerful
他才能夠在這麼強大的
Stick to a certain kind of trend in an era
一個時代的潮流裡面去堅守某一種
what he believes
他認為的信念
then finally
那麼最後
as a conclusion
作為結論
get out of the house
走出家門
Travel from abroad
來自於國門的旅行
life journey
人生的旅行
literary travel
文學的旅行
China travel experience
中國旅行的旅行的經驗
In fact, there are various
其實有各式各樣的
face
面貌
My speech today is just to choose
我今天的演講只是選擇了
Lu Bicheng's European and American Tours
呂碧城的歐美賣遊路
as the center
作為中心
Of course this is because
當然這是因為
character who goes by himself
他自己去的人物
Also because of his works to this day
也因為他的作品直到今天
let us appreciate
都有讓我們欣賞
complete place
完位之處
And more noticeably
而更可以注意的是
active in the 19th century
作為活躍於19世紀
turn of the second century
末二世世紀初之交的
women of literature
文學的女性
Lu Bicheng, I think
呂碧城我覺得
really has some kind of key meaning
真的具有某一種關鍵的意義
he obviously
他顯然
cant
不能夠
simply to inspire
簡簡單單的以啟蒙
progress
進步
We are more simplistic today
我們今天比較單一化的
label to define him
標籤來定義他
why
為什麼呢
Because from some of the examples we just climbed
因為從我們剛才所爬書的一些例子
you can see
就可以看到
It actually continues upwards
它往上其實是承續著
The literary aesthetics of classical women
古典女性的那種文學 審美
And a heart and will to explore outward
以及向外探索的一種心靈跟意志
Down it actually opened the modern
往下它其實開啟了現代
We can even say that it means contemporary
甚至我們可以說當代的一種意味的
Roaming New Meaning of Travel
漫遊 新的旅行的意義
The travels it does and the writing it mails
它所實行的旅行以及它郵寄的書寫
the kind of many women of its generation
與它同代的許多女性的那種
purposeful travel
具有目的性的旅遊
In fact, there is a separation
其實是有所取隔的
I want to use a special example today
我想今天就以一個比較特殊的例子
Back and forth to the Ming and Qing Dynasties
來回溯到明清時期
and down to our contemporary experience
以及往下拉到我們當代的經驗
Share it with everyone
跟大家分享一下
My observations and understanding of Chinese women's travel experience
我對於中國女性的旅行經驗的一些觀察理解
with feelings
跟感想
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you for talking nonsense
謝謝胡說長
then he speaks brilliantly
那麼他講得很精采
we have about ten minutes
我們有十分鐘左右
I don't know who's going to finish
我不知道誰要結完
good time
好好時間
Simple
簡單
short
簡短一點
if there is a problem, just say
有問題就是說
just said it again and again
剛剛再三講到說
he is classified as handy
他被歸類為手就派
because of his problem
因為他的問題
But his hands are so-called, they are actually too attractive
但是他的手是所謂其實也太吸引了
Those who criticized him at the time
那當時批評他為手就派的人
rebellious for his attraction
對於他吸引而叛逆
he doesn't want to start hurtful behavior
他不想開傷性的行為
Don't you think your criticism is contradictory?
不覺得自己的批評是矛盾的嗎
What do these critics think of
這些批評者怎麼樣去看待
His behavior attracts hands with his questions
他的行為的吸引跟他的問題的手
so this thing
所以這件事情
Thanks
謝謝
What I just said is actually a
我剛才說的其實也是一個
The name of the later construction
後建之名的說法
His contemporaries don't think so
他當代人不這麼覺得
For example he was
比方說他當時
Posted in so many news
登在這麼多的新聞
What was in the media at the time
什麼的在當時的媒體上面
It's what I just said is very popular.
就是我剛才說的是非常受到歡迎的
So we'll see in hindsight
所以我們以後見之明說
When we went to see him in later literary history
我們後來的文學史裡面去看他的時候
will be like this
才會這樣被
He would be classified as such
他才會這樣被歸類為
what old hands
以什麼手舊啦
Or can't innovate
或者是不能夠創新啦
Or let's say what we see in contemporary times
或者是比方說我們在當代看到的
a modern critic would say
現代的批評會說
in his overseas neologisms
他的海外新詞裡面
Although I have written so many Western things
雖然寫了那麼多的西方的東西
but just one
但是就是一個
he never left
他從來都沒有脫離過
his Chinese classical
他的中國的古典
we will see criticism like this
我們會看到這樣的批評
with his western sword
跟他的西方的劍文
the spark
所擦出來的那個火花
that's where it gets interesting
才是有趣的地方
It’s not that he must give up Chinese classical
並不是他一定要放棄中國的古典
Or he must embrace the western Jianwen
或是他一定要擁抱著西方的劍文
that genre follows
那個文類跟
The one produced between his sword texts
他的那個劍文之間所產生的那個
The contradiction is
矛盾之處是
is where he's really interesting
是他真正有趣的地方
personally
個人來看
ask for advice
請教教少
Just mentioned that Li Bichen
剛剛提到說那個李碧晨
he
他
before going to san francisco
要到舊金山之前
used to visit
曾經去遊覽
he went to san francisco first
他先去了舊金山
not go first
不是先去
San Francisco
舊金山
then to
然後再到
His name is Luo Sheng
他叫羅省
Rosander
就是羅桑德
then go to hollywood
然後再去好萊塢
going to hollywood
去的好萊塢
Said he was dreaming
還說他做夢夢
Go to Nan Xingxing's business card and give him
到南明星地名片給他
Li Bichen
當時李碧晨
Did he ever yearn for
他是不是曾經有向往過
maybe
自己或許
gonna be a hollywood star
會成為好萊塢的明星
Is there such a record
有沒有這樣的記載
Thanks
謝謝
Is there such a record?
這樣的記載嗎
I don't seem to have seen such a record
我好像沒有看到這樣的記載
But he's really a star
不過他真的就是一個明星
except he's not hollywood
只不過他不是好萊塢
quiet star
靜的明星
Thank you very much for your thoughts
非常謝謝你的連想
Today you presented this
今天您呈現的這個
trip
旅行
But we also know that in the late 19th or early 20th century
但是我們也知道19世紀末或20世紀初
There are many Chinese laborers going to Southeast Asia or to Europe and the United States
有很多的中國勞工到東南亞或到歐美去
Then they are an underground class
那他們是一個地下的階層
Then it was also during this period that women began to
然後也是在這一段時間開始有女性
It may be because the male goes out first to follow the son or the husband.
可能是因為男性先出去是從子或是從夫
And to the United States or to Southeast Asia
而到了美國或者是到東南亞去
that their trip
那他們的旅行
If we take their outings as travel
如果我們以他們的出遊為旅行的話
their travel experience will be very different
他們的旅行經驗就會是非常不一樣
I don’t know if it’s in your research
那不曉得說在你的研究裡面
Is there any travel involved in this area?
有沒有涉及到這一塊的旅行
is underground
是地下階層的
This alarm is easy to guess
這個報警好猜到
sore feet because
痛腳因為
because i'm from doing this star feminist literature
因為我從做這個明星女性文學
Or until the end of the Qing Dynasty and the beginning of the Ming Dynasty
或者是一直到這個清末明初的這個
The phenomenon of some so-called female writers in the literary world
文壇的一些所謂的這個女作家的現象
I must admit I'm really relatively untouched by this upper middle class
我必須承認我真的比較沒有觸及這個中上階級
Beyond the experience of women's lives
以外的女性的生命的經驗
The one I'm sharing with you today
今天在我跟大家分享的那個
content
內容當中
at most it is about
最多就是有關於
Activities in Jingxiang
靜鄉的活動
Participated by non-elite women
是非菁英的女性參加的
But I must also regret to say
但是我也必須很遺憾地說
Just that example
剛好那個例子
also by male authors
也是由男性的作者
presented with a critical eye
用批判的眼光來呈現的
So as for women of that class
那麼至於那個階層的女性
when she engages in activities like that
當她從事那樣的活動的時候
her own
她自己的
no matter how
不管是
I feel good
內心的感受也好
She has good experience
她的經驗也好
I
我
I haven't done any research myself
我自己沒有做過研究
then i too
那麼我也
I have no idea
我不知道
what material to use
用什麼材料
can come to explore
可以來探索
this aspect of this matter
這一方面的這個事情
this is real
這個就真的
beyond my ability
在我能力之外
terribly sorry
很抱歉
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you, I’m the author and I can’t understand it, but it’s very interesting to listen to tonight
謝謝啊 我是文主跟不通 但是今天晚上聽得非常有趣
One problem I have is that your head is all purple
我有一個問題就是 你這個頭影都是紫色的
Your clothes are also purple, so it doesn't matter if I carry them
你的衣著也是紫色 所以我背也沒有關係
In fact, if my colleagues know that the background color of the POWER POINT I use recently is this color
其實如果像我的同事都知道 我最近使用的POWER POINT的底色都是這個顏色
Because I think it has a dark background, so it highlights the front
因為我覺得它底色很深 所以凸顯前面的東西
That's the only reason the dress was just casually worn this morning when it was too late
這是唯一原因 這個衣服就是今天早上來不及的時候隨便穿的
just a coincidence
就是碰巧而已
I think just now Director Hu showed the rich clothing images of women since the Ming and Qing Dynasties
我想剛才胡所長展現了明清以來女性的這個很豐富的衣服圖像
travel is a big subject i'm not researching this but travel is a big subject
旅行是一個大題目 我不是研究這個 不過旅行是個大題目
In 1932 or the 1930s, Academia Sinica had an early
1932幾年還是三年代 中研院最早期有一位
But he really seemed to be just an editor named Jiang Shaoyuan who wrote an article
但是他當時真的好像只是編輯員 叫江少元 寫了一篇
Ancient Chinese Travel Studies
中國古代行旅研究
Look inside and talk about ancient travel
裡面就看講古代旅行
full of superstition
充滿迷信
use many mysterious means
要用很多神秘的手段
To prevent bad luck from happening, etc.
才能阻止惡運的發生等等
So the whole trip is a
所以整個行旅是一個
A very complicated and dangerous process
很複雜很危險的一個過程
But this book pays little attention to
不過這本書還要注意得很少
But there are many books like this
不過像這類的書很多
It is also worth referring to our elves today
也很值得跟我們今天的精靈來參照
When painstaking efforts of Haruki are always fashionable
在經常朝陽明的心血在流行的時候
Travel is an important means for their spiritual progress
旅行就是他們精神進步很重要的手段
Because you have to meet different people when you go out
因為出去都要見到不同的人
different realms
都不同的境界
so travel
所以旅行
But it's different from what he said today
但是跟他今天講的這個是不一樣
Nonsense Zhang is talking about another stage
胡說張講的是另外一個階段
Another form of this trip
另一種形式這個旅行
I think he spoke very well today
我覺得他今天講得非常精彩
I've been watching what he's looking at paper
我一直在看他在看著紙是什麼
I thought there was an article
原來以為是有一篇稿
because he speaks well
因為他出口成章
He noticed that the birth of a child is a chapter of this
他注意到 產女出口成章 這個
Later I found out that there is no, he actually seems to be an article, right?
後來我才發現沒有 他其實好像是一篇文章是不是
is relevant
是相關的
related
相關的
related related material
相關的 相關的材料
Li Bicheng of course
李碧成當然有
I'm only here and there are a lot of things about him.
我才在座有很多對他大概多列之
Frankly speaking, I always thought he was with
坦白說我三四十年前一直以為他是跟
People like Hu Yingmeng
胡英夢一樣的人
Do you know Hu Yingmeng?
你們知道胡英夢這個人嗎
He and many important people in the late Qing Dynasty and the Republic of China
他跟晚清民國很多重要人
They all had contacts, and the earliest was with the most famous
都有來往 而且最早是跟當時最有名的
The latest sciences together, like logic, etc.
最新的學問在一起 像邏輯學等等
So there are many in the original father who are related to Li Bicheng
所以原父裡面有很多跟李碧成
Many people had two burns. The original father and others mentioned it.
很多人都兩起燒 原父等等都提了
But this Uncle Hu showed another name today.
可是這個胡叔叔今天展現的是另外一個名
I knew very little about this side
對這一面我原來知道的非常少
It's because I listened to his speech today.
因為今天聽他演講才略有所致
I'm very proud of myself, too. Thank you.
我個人也得意良多 謝謝
Well we just missed you today thank you
好 我們今天就是想念大家 謝謝
Thanks
謝謝